<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Roman empress a tragedy : acted at the Royal Theater, by His Majesties servants / and written by William Joyner, Gent.</title>
            <author>Joyner, William, 1622-1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 167 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46333</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J1159</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R695</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12305315</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12305315</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59228</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46333)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59228)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 637:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Roman empress a tragedy : acted at the Royal Theater, by His Majesties servants / and written by William Joyner, Gent.</title>
                  <author>Joyner, William, 1622-1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 67 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.N. for Henry Herringman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] In the Savoy :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First edition.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Supposed to be the story of Constantine the Great and his son Crispus.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Constantine --  I, --  Emperor of Rome, d. 337 --  Drama.</term>
               <term>Crispus, Flavius Julius, d. 326 --  Drama.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59228:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59228:1"/>
            <p>THE Roman Empreſs. A TRAGEDY: Acted at the ROYAL THEATER, BY HIS MAJESTIES SERVANTS. And written by <hi>WILLIAM JOYNER, Gent.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Qui Bavium non odit, amet tua carmina Maevi;</l>
               <l>Atque inopeis rerum verſus, nugaſque canoras.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Virg. Ecl. 3. Horat.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>In the <hi>SAVOY,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. N.</hi> for <hi>Henry Herringman,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Sign of the Anchor in the lower Walk of the <hi>New Exchange,</hi> 1671.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:59228:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59228:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONORABLE S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Charles Sidley.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough this Tragedy, in ſpight of a dead Vacation, and ſome other impediments, found the applauſe &amp; approbation of the Theater as oft as it appear'd: yet I eſteem it a ſingular fortune to have had yours in particular: and look upon it like the great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, which a rich jewel gives to a ring of gold. Such envious ſpirits, who thought nothing requiſite, but au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacity, to become Cenſors in this Art (which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance is the ſubtileſt of human invention) and upon this ground condemn'd the common ſuffrage: when they ſee it confirm'd by yours, will loſe the choiceſt fruits of their malice. In the government of Provinces under <hi>Nero,</hi> 'tis obſerv'd, that it was alwayes dangerous to do well; and yet not ſtill ſafe to do ill. Theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons would bring the Stage to the ſame condition: for as they have ſought to condemn this Play for the regular conformity to the rules of art, and reaſon; ſo they have not deſiſted ſometimes to decry others for their unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural
<pb facs="tcp:59228:3"/>incongruities, when they have been inform'd where they are. Sir I could wiſh that you, ſo far plac'd above the reach of envy, would honor the Theater with ſome productions of this nature: For there is nothing more difficult; or which requires a more elevated wit, richer fancy, or ſubtiler judgement: Which rare qualities con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur in you in ſo high a perfection, that there is no free, noble ſoul which denyes you herein the juſt tribute of reſpect and preference. In the happy return, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of our great Soveraign, we ſee reſtor'd to us the ſecure felicity of the times of <hi>Augustus.</hi> To which you might add the ſplendour, by affording us the noble fruits and inventions of your wit. <hi>Meſſala Corvinus,</hi> and <hi>Pollio,</hi> the Ornaments of that Court, though eminent in War, prefer'd this way to perpetuate the glory of their names: A deſire which naturally inflames Heroical breſts; and ſhould do yours: the commendation of the preſent times being a Patrimony of too contracted li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits for ſo great a worth: which cannot receive deſerv'd fame and reputation, but from the bounty of ſucceeding ages: which I much wiſh, and at preſent, the continua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a flouriſhing proſperity. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt humble and obliged Servant, <hi>WILLIAM JOYNER.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:59228:3"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving conſider'd, that of all Tragedies the old <hi>Oedipus,</hi> in the just eſtimation of the Antients and Moderns carry'd the Crown: a Story as yet untoucht by any <hi>Engliſh</hi> Pen; I thought, though defective in my art, I could not be but very fortunate in this my ſubject. Which has given me leave not only to include what is admirable in this <hi>Oedipus;</hi> but ſeveral great advantages above it for a Tragical Theater. Of which, one is the greatneſs of this <hi>Roman</hi> Emperour above ſo petty a Prince in <hi>Greece.</hi> Another is, that tis imagin'd, there was never any ſuch perſon as this <hi>Oedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> and the Story wholy fabulous. Whereas mine is found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in truth and reality. For, though by adviſe of friends I have diſguiſ'd the names; yet this Emperour was one of the greateſt that ever <hi>Rome</hi> boasted. He held his Adverſary ſometime reduc'd to that low condition and poſture I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe. And inſtigated by this malicious calumny of his Empreſs, put to death his own Son, after the creating of him <hi>Caeſar.</hi> As it was affirm'd by the glorious Martyr <hi>Artemius</hi> in the preſence of the Emperour <hi>Julian</hi> Apostate: Who was the near Kinſman of this <hi>Florus;</hi> and very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitive after the ſad end of ſo brave and illuſtrious a Perſon. Yet ſome Hiſtorians make him die accuſ'd for Treaſon: and I for both; with the moſt forcible reaſons I could produce. For intending <hi>Valentius</hi> for my Protago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt,
<pb facs="tcp:59228:4"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the moſt perfect ſubject of Tragical compaſſion in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> approv'd by all intelligent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtrangely to circumvent him; and make the moſt excuſable, I poſſibly could, that imprudence for which <hi>Zoſimus</hi> maliciouſly defames him. Beſides this Character of <hi>Oedipus,</hi> the true occurrents of this admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Story afford me two others highly celebrated by all learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Nations, in the perſons of <hi>Fulvia,</hi> and <hi>Florus,</hi> who much repreſents the old <hi>Hippolytus,</hi> unleſs it be in the horrid rudeneſs of his carriage; which I have here chang'd into a gallant bravery, ending in a diſmal Cataſtrophe, much more agreeable to the compaſſion of theſe Times. The antient <hi>Phoedra</hi> is here ſet off in a real <hi>Fulvia;</hi> and I am inform'd, ſome exceptions are taken at the wickedneſs I ſhew in her perſon: but ſure theſe people want a ſubject of diſcourſe, and trouble, who would fain concern themſelves in my not concealing the ill qualities of a Pagan woman: who for the atrocity of theſe crimes is known in Hiſtory to have had a miſerable end. This Character has been ever much extoll'd: if my art has fail'd in the writing of it, it was highly recompenc'd in the ſcenical preſentation; for it was incomparably acted. I have for the greater variety of the Stage divided this Character, conferring ſome ſhare of it on <hi>Aurelia,</hi> which, though a great, various, and difficult part, was excellently performed. In the perſon of <hi>Honori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> I have nothing of antiquity to plead for me, the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter being never thought of by any man but by ſelf: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had I honour'd him with ſuch noble company, but by the advice of ſome friends; who perſwaded me, that his horrid opinions, by reaſon of the novelty, and the ſetting off
<pb facs="tcp:59228:4"/>a falſe Pagan Gallantry, would excellently ſuit with this Tragical Subject. At which no juſt exceptions can be taken, for none ſure come to Playes to learn true history, or religion; and to make profane perſons ſpeake profanely, is practiſ'd in the Tragedies of <hi>Petavius;</hi> whom I my ſelf knew as emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent for his piety, as learning.</p>
            <p>If the language pleaſe not, I am ſorry: the fault proceeds from no want of reſpect to the Audience. For I wrote the quantity of three or four Playes upon this noble Subject; of which I conceive this the beſt extract. Such who expect to have their ears tickled with the gingling Antitheſes of Love and Honor, and ſuch like petty wares, will find themſelves deceiv'd. For the chief intent of Tragedy being to raiſe Terror and Compaſſion; I thought a more maſculine and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous eloquence and graces more natural, and leſs affected, were requiſite to inſpire ſuch impreſſions. For ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Stage, which delights in variety, I have ſought to entertain the Audience with the divertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of new accidents; not only from Act to Act, but Scene to Scene; where the Conteſts are lively, the Paſſions vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, the Deſignes extreme, and the Deliberations horrid. My endeavour has been to conform this piece to the beſt rules of Art in all the parts: Though my Oppoſers have preſum'd to condemn it cleer throughout: but eſpecially in the fifth Act, which they have concluded ſenſeleſs, and void of all art and reaſon; With which (as the head of man is with intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual faculties) it ſhould be chiefly enricht. And ſo the Reader ſhall perceive it, if he pleaſe rather to direct him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by the rules of ſolid Science; then the dreams of theſe Perſons. For here he finds himſelf arriv'd at the end of
<pb facs="tcp:59228:5"/>ſtrangely astoniſhing diſaſters; yet confin'd within the limits of Probability; without having the leaſt reaſon to demand how he has been conducted, or by what means they have been wrought. Though in the paſſage (as I may ſay) they have been wholy ſurpriſing, and left him every where at a loſs. This rule I have obſerv'd throughout the Play, to pleaſe the judicious, who ſtill watch and expect things unexpected: And I believe will ſcarce find here one anticipated action, or event. For the Dream of <hi>Valentius,</hi> though it ſeems to give a manifeſt overture of the conſequence, yet the obſcure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is ſo dark, that it deceives not only Him, but the very Audience; the fatal thunderbolt falling, unſeen and unheard in the midſt of them. And here occurs in the Perſon of <hi>Valentius,</hi> what <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> admires in <hi>Oedipus,</hi> confeſſing human wit can invent in this kind nothing beyond it. For he incurs thoſe very misfortunes, which with all ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable care he ſhun'd; condemning his Son without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him; and after death knowing him without all benefit: which makes him the beſt, and greatest of all Tragical Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. The narration I have made cleer, pathetique, and ſhort; including a ſtory curious, and therefore not taedious: To ſhun which fault I have alſo interrupted it with the dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful exclamation of <hi>Valentius</hi> in the Agnition of his Error: Which to judicious ears appears the moſt melodious part in Tragical compoſition. In the eſcape of <hi>Fulvia</hi> I have fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd the example of <hi>Medea,</hi> which by the ſubtile and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious <hi>Caſtelvetro</hi> is only cenſur'd for the want of prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratives: the foregoing parts having nothing contributed to this strange action. Which is here contrary; and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance more rational. Which my oppoſers ſhould have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markt.
<pb facs="tcp:59228:5"/>And how the great Cataſtrophes in this Play pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from no external helps, or new faces unſeen before; but from the interweaving of the intrinſecal parts of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; And how I have not defil'd the Majeſtique Grace of a Tragique Theater with the company of any vile Plebeian Perſons, though the Plot has been ſo variouſly intricated. They ſhould laſtly have taken notice, that here is nothing Epiſodical; which I have not made eſſential in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the Story; from whence ariſes the graceful Vnion: An obſervation to be wiſht more in faſhion. For it is this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, which like Harmony in Muſique, gives the laſt perfection and beauty to all Subjects moral, as well as natural.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:59228:6"/>
            <head>DRAMATIS PERSONAE.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>VAlentius,</hi> Roman Emperour.
<list>
                     <item>Major <hi>Mohun.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Florus,</hi> whoſe other name is <hi>Veſpaſius,</hi> General of <hi>Valentius;</hi> proving at laſt to be his Son.
<list>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Kynaſton.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Honorius,</hi> Friend of <hi>Florus: Epicurean</hi> in his opinions.
<list>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Bell.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Statilius,</hi> A Military Councellor, and Favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of <hi>Valentius.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Lyddel.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Macrinus,</hi> A great Perſon, vulgarly paſſing for the Father of <hi>Florus.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Beeſton.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Servilius,</hi> Great Courtiers, and Commanders of Legions.
<list>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Harris.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Carbo,</hi> Great Courtiers, and Commanders of Legions.
<list>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Littlewood.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fulvia,</hi> Roman Empreſs, in love with <hi>Florus.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>The young M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>. <hi>Marſhall.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Antonia,</hi> Lady of Honor to <hi>Fulvia,</hi> and Wife to <hi>Servilius.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Mrs. <hi>Kneap.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hoſtilius,</hi> Tyrant of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Watſon.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Arſenius,</hi> General of <hi>Hoſtilius,</hi> and thinking himſelf Father of <hi>Florus.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Cartwright.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Aurelia,</hi> Daughter of <hi>Hoſtilius,</hi> of ſingular beauty, belov'd of <hi>Florus.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> 
                        <hi>Boutell.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sophonia,</hi> Her Governeſs; who proves to be <hi>Palladia,</hi> firſt Wife of <hi>Valentius,</hi> ſuppoſed long before dead.
<list>
                     <item>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> 
                        <hi>Cory.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Courts, Men, Women, Officers, Attendants, &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The <hi>SCENE</hi> of this Drama or Action is about the Banks of <hi>Tiber:</hi> where <hi>Hoſtilius</hi> and his Party are ſuppoſ'd to be in <hi>Rome,</hi> or on the <hi>Roman</hi> ſide of the River: And <hi>Valentius</hi> with his Party encampt on the other ſide in the nature of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiegers.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59228:6"/>
            <head>THE Roman Empreſs.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>ACT. I.</head>
               <stage>Hoſtilius, Courtier, and Court-Attendants.</stage>
               <stage>The SCENE expoſ'd of a Battle newly fought.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <l>THe Enemy, Sir, is at laſt retreated</l>
                  <l>Almoſt with equal loſs, after a cruel</l>
                  <l>And bloody fight, excepting that young <hi>Lucius.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Prince of the Roman Youth, and your brave Son,</l>
                  <l>As yet appears not: your Camp-maſter below</l>
                  <l>Attends to give you an exact relation.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hoſt.</speaker>
                  <l>I come: in the mean ſpace ſee that my Daughter</l>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Aurelia, Sophonia.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>Attend me here:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Co.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall — Madam I was</l>
                  <l>Juſt coming to inform your Princely Highneſs,</l>
                  <l>How his Imperial Majeſty intends</l>
                  <l>To find you in this place.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <p>Depart. He ſhall</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Sophonia. Aurelia weeping.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, I ſhould eſteem the tears you ſhed</l>
                  <l>At a great value, did they eaſe thoſe griefs</l>
                  <l>They thus lament: but they rather increaſe them:</l>
                  <l>Clear thoſe bright lights then from thoſe miſty clouds.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:59228:7"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>—My dear <hi>Sophonia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe milk firſt gave me bloud, whoſe boſom, life;</l>
                  <l>Add this to thoſe thy other benefits,</l>
                  <l>To let me thus conſume my ſelf in tears</l>
                  <l>Which are ſo juſt: thou ſeeſt</l>
                  <l>My Fathers power, which lately had no other</l>
                  <l>Bounds, than the boundleſs Ocean, and the Heavens</l>
                  <l>Contracted to the Walls of <hi>Rome,</hi> confin'd</l>
                  <l>Here to the Banks of <hi>Tiber;</hi> where we ſuffer</l>
                  <l>Defeats upon defeats, no funerals ſee</l>
                  <l>Of Parents, Friends, Allies; which make not up</l>
                  <l>Their horrid train with funerals of others.</l>
                  <l>I fear the iſſue of this cruel fight,</l>
                  <l>Wherein my Brother was engag'd. New horror,</l>
                  <l>Beſides from ill preſages of my mind</l>
                  <l>Torments my fancy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Soph.</speaker>
                  <l>Theſe thoughts and fears unworthy are to enter</l>
                  <l>The breaſt of my <hi>Aurelia,</hi> but are inmates</l>
                  <l>Fit to be entertain'd by ſuch are born</l>
                  <l>To the diſtaff and obedience: you the Daughter</l>
                  <l>And Niece of Emperors, markt with the ſtamp</l>
                  <l>Of Majeſty Imperial, and of Beauty,</l>
                  <l>Are deſtin'd, when that <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall chooſe her Head,</l>
                  <l>To be Commandreſs of that great Commander,</l>
                  <l>Or rather by the honor of your bed</l>
                  <l>To ſhew who's proper to be <hi>Romes</hi> great Head.</l>
                  <l>Compoſe your ſelf, your tears and grief aſſwage</l>
                  <l>By timely marriage, and ſtop this civil rage.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>From funeral, to thoſe of nuptial rites,</l>
                  <l>The paſſage will ſeem ſtrange: the heavens change not</l>
                  <l>So ſuddenly, but 'twixt the day and night</l>
                  <l>They interpoſe the mornings dusky light.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Soph.</speaker>
                  <l>The morning's gay and pleaſant, diſſipates<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nights horror; ſo let mirth begin in you</l>
                  <l>A day of jollity, which may not know</l>
                  <l>What ſetting is.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Which to me cannot happen; thou haſt known</l>
                  <l>My heart, <hi>Sophonia,</hi> and what a cruel part</l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:59228:7"/>
                  <l>Love there has acted; for I told thee how</l>
                  <l>When I laſt paſſed to the Enemies Camp</l>
                  <l>In my diſguiſe (as I muſt now again)</l>
                  <l>I fell in love with <hi>Florus</hi> their brave Gen'ral,</l>
                  <l>And ſo became a captive of the greateſt</l>
                  <l>Oppreſſor of our Cauſe, and Family.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Soph.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, <hi>Arſenius</hi> has inform'd you how</l>
                  <l>He's more ſurpriz'd with you; ſo that two flames</l>
                  <l>Love never better kindled, to extinguiſh</l>
                  <l>This mortal hatred of your Families.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>True, if the cruel nature of my Father,</l>
                  <l>Who thirſts after his bloud, would not oppoſe us.</l>
                  <l>But here he comes; and as my fears foretel me,</l>
                  <l>To reprehend me on this very ſubject.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>To them Hoſtilius and Macrinus.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hoſ.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Macrinus,</hi> when the Romans ſurfeited</l>
                  <l>With Roman bloud, think fit to ſtop the torrent,</l>
                  <l>You like a generous adverſary will</l>
                  <l>Advance the publick good: <hi>Mac.</hi> 'Tis my firſt wiſh</l>
                  <l>Thus to expreſs my gratitude to you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hoſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Farewel, and, where the laws of arms permit you,</l>
                  <l>Be civil to my party. Now <hi>Sophonia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Macr.</stage>
                  <l>Your obligations to <hi>Macrinus</hi> are</l>
                  <l>Cancell'd by this his liberty, I give him;</l>
                  <l>Which though you do not, I count forfeited.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sop.</speaker>
                  <p>I muſt eternally record this favour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hoſ.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aurelia,</hi> 'twas you, and your intreaty</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Soph.</stage>
                  <l>I ſought to gratifie herein: I hope</l>
                  <l>When I grant your requeſt, that you will mine,</l>
                  <l>Which is at preſent, to caſt off thoughts of love,</l>
                  <l>Eſpecially of <hi>Florus;</hi> an Uſurper,</l>
                  <l>As in the State, ſo in thy breaſt now enterd,</l>
                  <l>Where love muſt have no harbor: I ſhall find</l>
                  <l>Paſſions more noble to poſſeſs thy mind.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, if external beauty joyn'd with virtue</l>
                  <l>Force love in womans heart, it is no wonder.</l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:59228:8"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Florus</hi> finds entrance here: Sir, let theſe tears</l>
                  <l>Soften that breaſt, which the age, war, and cuſtom</l>
                  <l>Seem to have armed ſo againſt compaſſion.</l>
                  <l>— When you reflect</l>
                  <l>On loves predominancy over all things,</l>
                  <l>Can you imagin that the ſoft and tender</l>
                  <l>Breaſt of a young and inexperienc'd Virgin</l>
                  <l>Can reſiſt him, who under the white ſnow</l>
                  <l>Of reverend gray-heads, kindles his fires,</l>
                  <l>and with his flames, extinguiſhes the light</l>
                  <l>Of the matureſt judgements.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hoſ.</speaker>
                  <l>— Love exerciſes</l>
                  <l>His power only where he finds conſent.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No April tree when her green ſeaſon's paſt</l>
                     <l>Shoots not forth into bloſſoms; nor no Virgin,</l>
                     <l>Her Spring time come, feels not the heats of love.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>However O my erring ſoul, and thou</l>
                     <l>My captiv'd heart, and you my thus miſplac'd</l>
                     <l>Affections bear me witneſs, if I uſ'd not</l>
                     <l>(To comply with my Father) all my forces</l>
                     <l>To free my mind from theſe tyrannick paſſions:</l>
                     <l>But O alas! the more I ſought to break</l>
                     <l>Theſe fetters, I in them was more intangled.</l>
                     <l>This love which in my breaſt inſenſibly</l>
                     <l>It ſelf inſinuating, there grew up</l>
                     <l>Without adviſe of reaſon, can't be now</l>
                     <l>By reaſon either govern'd, or extinguiſht.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hoſ.</speaker>
                  <l>— Audacious creature, were I not (what thou</l>
                  <l>Seems't to deny here) an indulgent Father,</l>
                  <l>Thou from theſe hands at preſent ſhouldſt receive</l>
                  <stage>ſhews her his ſword.</stage>
                  <l>Chaſtiſement proper to thy inſolence,</l>
                  <l>Which now falls on thee mitigated onely</l>
                  <l>Into admoniſhment; thy error is</l>
                  <l>Th' error of love, which is excuſable</l>
                  <l>In younger age, confined within limits</l>
                  <l>Excuſable; but when a royal Princeſs</l>
                  <l>Hurri'd from love to madneſs by her paſſion</l>
                  <l>Diſdains the curbs of reaſon, and of honor,</l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:59228:8"/>
                  <l>And yields her ſelf up to my greateſt foe,</l>
                  <l>This is a crime ſeverely to be puniſht;</l>
                  <l>and ſhould be, were I not aſſur'd of thy</l>
                  <l>Future amendment: but in the mean time</l>
                  <stage>Gives her a bloody handkerchif.</stage>
                  <l>Wipe off thy tears, for <hi>Florus</hi> here with this.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>What ominous gift is this?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hoſ.</speaker>
                  <l>It is a token</l>
                  <stage>She ſtartles.</stage>
                  <l>Dipt in thy Brother <hi>Lucius</hi> bloud, with which</l>
                  <l>The hands of <hi>Florus,</hi> as yet hot, and diſtilling,</l>
                  <l>Muſt thee embrace.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Death ſhall embrace me firſt</l>
                  <l>In her cold arms. What mutiny is here?</l>
                  <l>One of my chiefeſt vital parts has me</l>
                  <l>Depriv'd of th' other. Oh, my Brother ſlain!</l>
                  <l>And by the hands of <hi>Florus,</hi> juſt when he</l>
                  <l>Has ſignifi'd his flames reciprocal,</l>
                  <l>And great as mine. O my accurſed fate!</l>
                  <l>Why, we were twins, bedfollows in the womb,</l>
                  <l>Companions e're born, together united</l>
                  <l>Before with life inſpired: in his death</l>
                  <l>I've loſt my better part, and can't ſurvive</l>
                  <stage>She falls into a ſwoun.</stage>
                  <l>With what is left me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hoſ.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aurelia,</hi> nay <hi>Aurelia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Recall thy ſelf, thy Father is yet living</l>
                  <stage>He ſtrives to recover her.</stage>
                  <l>Thy loving Father, who to thee ſhall be</l>
                  <l>A Brother, Mother, all things; reaſſume</l>
                  <l>Thy life and courage.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>I do, and find my ſelf</l>
                  <stage>She ſeems to come to her ſelf.</stage>
                  <l>In this ſhort tranſe ſo chang'd, that now I'm ſorry</l>
                  <l>I have no pentitential moiſture left</l>
                  <l>To expiate thoſe tears, againſt my duty,</l>
                  <l>Caſt away on the love of <hi>Florus:</hi> but</l>
                  <l>You'll pardon this defect; deſire of my</l>
                  <l>Revenge ſo agitates my heart, and raiſeth</l>
                  <l>Such violent motions in my troubled fancy</l>
                  <l>Tranſporting all my thoughts, and faculties</l>
                  <l>To her tyrannique will; like ſome vaſt flame,</l>
                  <l>Which all occurring obſtacles conſuming,</l>
                  <l>Transformeth them at laſt into her ſelf.</l>
                  <l>Rage, choller, fury, ofsprings of hell increaſe</l>
                  <l>And multiply here in this breaſt, which freely</l>
                  <l>I open to you, caſting out all thoughts</l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:59228:9"/>
                  <l>Of virgin ſoftneſs, or remorſe; hereafter</l>
                  <l>Theſe fountains of my eyes be ever dry;</l>
                  <l>My hands, and tongue audacious to commit</l>
                  <l>Miſchiefs to terrifie mankind; my looks</l>
                  <l>Diſſembling, treacherous, and fatal be</l>
                  <l>To thoſe they pleaſe; the powers of my ſoul</l>
                  <l>Let my rage rule, and nothing it controul.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hoſ.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aurelia,</hi> now thou ſhew'ſt, thou doſt inherit,</l>
                  <l>As well as Mothers beauty, Fathers ſpirit.</l>
                  <l>Magnanimous revenge, not love's a gueſt</l>
                  <l>Fit to be harbor'd in a royal breſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Sophonia. Macrinus.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Soph.</speaker>
                  <l>O dear <hi>Macrinus,</hi> haſten thy departure,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hoſtilius</hi> muſt not know thy longer ſtay,</l>
                  <l>He thinks he gives, what he can take away,</l>
                  <l>Thy liberty, which I have ſo endanger'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mac.</speaker>
                  <l>I would expoſe my life, much more what you</l>
                  <l>Call liberty, to ſerve your Majeſty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Soph.</speaker>
                  <l>That word does but revive</l>
                  <l>The memory of my unhappy fate,</l>
                  <stage>Macr. <hi>weeps.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>Which I would fain forget. I prethee weep not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mac.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, I muſt, though I rejoyce to ſee</l>
                  <l>Your virtue triumph o're your miſery.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Soph.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou ſeeſt <hi>Valentius</hi> finds his ſatisfaction</l>
                  <l>In my ſuppoſed death.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mac.</speaker>
                  <l>The Gods we ſee</l>
                  <l>Intend your happineſs, ſince ſure by their</l>
                  <l>Inſtinct he deſtines <hi>Florus</hi> for the Throne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sop.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Macrinus,</hi> thou wouldſt fain revive my falſe</l>
                  <l>And treacherous hopes; but oh, I fear the heavens,</l>
                  <l>Which ſee mee in my miſeries grow old,</l>
                  <l>Will in them let me die: but pray lets ſee</l>
                  <l>The way th' haſt found (excuſe my vanity)</l>
                  <l>To ſave my reputation when I dye.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mac.</speaker>
                  <p>Here's the Inſcription which I have made of you.</p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:59228:9"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>The moſt unfortunate of women, the ſuppoſ'd</hi> Sophonia, <hi>was the true</hi> Palladia, <hi>Empreſs, and Wife of</hi> Valentius, <hi>condemn'd by him upon a falſe ſuſpicion, but ſav'd by</hi> Macrinus <hi>conſcious of her inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence and virtue, in teſtimony whereof he hath left theſe characters ingraved with his own hands.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>This I have cut in ſeveral plates of braſs,</l>
                  <l>Which fixt in walls, and only incruſted over</l>
                  <l>With a ſlight plaiſter, in ſhort time decaying,</l>
                  <l>Will clear your ſtory to the abuſed world.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Soph.</speaker>
                  <l>Honeſt <hi>Macrinus,</hi> how much I fear</l>
                  <l>I never ſhall this zeal of thine repay:</l>
                  <l>Once more farewel, make ſpeedy haſt away.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Florus. Servilius. Carbo.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Carb.</speaker>
                  <l>— Though Courts have ever been</l>
                  <l>The chiefeſt Theaters where love delights</l>
                  <l>To repreſent his cruel, ſerious follies:</l>
                  <l>Yet Camps are not exempted.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, Sir, but</l>
                  <l>The wonder is to ſee our noble Gen'ral</l>
                  <l>Surpriz'd thus with the picture of a Lady.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>Why were you ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, when the Roman Eagles</l>
                  <l>Victoriouſly under my conduct flew</l>
                  <l>Through <hi>Italy,</hi> reducing the Enemies power</l>
                  <l>To the Precincts of <hi>Rome;</hi> in the ſurpriſal</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Sarnium,</hi> I ſaw the picture of a Lady,</l>
                  <l>Drawn by the pencil of the famous <hi>Sanga,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſhape the very Goddeſſes would take,</l>
                  <l>Were they to make love here on earth again:</l>
                  <l>Ah how this object in the very moment</l>
                  <l>Depriv'd me of my liberty, ſo that</l>
                  <l>My entrance there was ſervile, not triumphal.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>To ſee ariſe in a great General</l>
                  <l>Confuſion from a Picture, from a ſhadow,</l>
                  <l>Is very ſtrange.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>I thought</l>
                  <l>A painted fire might deceive the ſight</l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:59228:10"/>
                  <l>But never raiſe a heat, or kindle flames.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>I grant this; did not fame</l>
                  <l>Paint out th' original ſubſtance of this ſhadow</l>
                  <l>Above what fancy comprehends; <hi>Eumolpus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Has on this ſubject made a Song, wherein</l>
                  <l>He'has toucht the proper ſtring of my affection,</l>
                  <l>With commendation of his friend the Painter.</l>
                  <l>Boy, lets ſee it, go now, and ſing it.</l>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="song">
                              <head>SONG.</head>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>That divine form which thus deludes thy ſenſe,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>And holds thee gazing in a ſtrange ſuſpence,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>The creature only is of</hi> Sanga's <hi>art;</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Yet from theſe eyes love does his fires dart.</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>To them a lively ſpeech his fav'ring hand</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>(Which to the tongue he never would impart)</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Has giv'n like Sirens to betray thy heart.</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Ah flye then! 'tis too late; thou haſt thy wound,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>And there doſt panting lye upon the ground.</hi>
                              </l>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <l>My ſtrange misfortune is, that I,</l>
                  <l>Or rather my ill fate, have fixt my love</l>
                  <l>Upon an Enemy of <hi>Valentius;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So that if I purſue it, I ſhall loſe</l>
                  <l>My Princes favour; and if not, I loſe</l>
                  <l>My ſoul, my ſelf.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Why he is ſick of my diſeaſe, I love</l>
                  <l>An Enemy of <hi>Valentius;</hi> to Thee</l>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aurelia</hi> I gave my faith before.</l>
                  <l>Thy Father was declar'd his enemy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>I muſt condem this love.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis then with high injuſtice.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>—He's guilty who hates not</l>
                  <l>His Princes Enemies; can you think him</l>
                  <l>Then innocent, who thus adores them.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>—Have patience only, and</l>
                  <l>Conſider if th' admirer of this object.</l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:59228:10"/>
                  <l>Rather deſerves reproach, pity, or envy</l>
                  <stage>ſhews a picture to them.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>—Whats this I ſee!</l>
                  <stage>aſide ſtartling.</stage>
                  <l>I have defended here my Rival; this</l>
                  <l>Is my <hi>Aurelia's</hi> picture, which I left her</l>
                  <l>A pledge of my eternal love at parting.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>This image ſo confounds my reaſon, that</l>
                  <l>Th' accuſed may juſtly abſolve himſelf</l>
                  <stage>aſide ſurpriz'd.</stage>
                  <l>By virtue of his Judges crime; I muſt</l>
                  <l>Think of my duty to my Wife and Prince.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>—I perceive ſtrange emotion</l>
                  <l>In them, but would not from their weakneſs ſeek</l>
                  <l>Protection for my failings. Why thus chang'd?</l>
                  <l>Come in, and recollect your ſelves, I'le ſee</l>
                  <l>If you are ſick of my infirmity.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Arſenius. Honorius.</stage>
               <stage>Arſ. <hi>diſguiſ'd in habit of a common ſouldier.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arſ.</speaker>
                  <l>—Behold us here arriv'd</l>
                  <l>At the Tents of <hi>Valentius;</hi> that I,</l>
                  <l>The General of <hi>Hoſtilius,</hi> diſguiſ'd</l>
                  <l>In this vile habit of a common Souldier,</l>
                  <l>Expoſe my ſelf to him my Enemy,</l>
                  <l>Are ſtrange effects of love: that liberty</l>
                  <l>—Which I give thee,</l>
                  <l>Thou in requital ſeems't to take from me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, that you have reſtor'd me to my ſelf</l>
                  <l>And liberty, I muſt confeſs, but not</l>
                  <l>That I thus ſeek to recompence your favour;</l>
                  <l>Expreſs your meaning: theſe words offend my honor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arſ.</speaker>
                  <l>You have oft told me that</l>
                  <l>Your General <hi>Florus</hi> was your greateſt friend;</l>
                  <l>On which belief I let you know he was</l>
                  <l>My only Son; and how capricious fortune</l>
                  <l>Had ſeparated thoſe minds, and affections</l>
                  <l>Which nature joyn'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis true, and I acquainted</l>
                  <l>You with his love of your Princeſs <hi>Aurelia;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Well knowing the advantages you would</l>
                  <l>Take to ſeduce him from his loyalty,</l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:59228:11"/>
                  <l>With ſo fair a temptation; but know</l>
                  <l>To this I then conſented, fearing, that</l>
                  <l>To take from noble vertue the occaſion</l>
                  <l>Of victory, was to envy her triumphing.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arſ.</speaker>
                  <l>I hope his love of her will now extort</l>
                  <l>That which the duty of a Father could not,</l>
                  <l>That's his obedience; ſince love ever finds</l>
                  <l>His Empire greateſt in the greateſt minds:</l>
                  <l>—though hitherto</l>
                  <l>The vain and empty title of being loyal</l>
                  <l>Prevail'd more with him then the entreaties of</l>
                  <l>A moſt indulgent and a tender father.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, you are too indulgent, who would thus</l>
                  <l>Permit, nay more perſwade him to become</l>
                  <l>A Traitor to his Prince, the common Father</l>
                  <l>Of us, and of his Country; and in whoſe</l>
                  <l>Obedience, though with loſs of life, and fortune,</l>
                  <l>He's happy in performing thus his duty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Of all wild beaſts, which entrance find in Courts,</l>
                  <l>Malicious detractors are the worſt:</l>
                  <l>Of all domeſtical, theſe flatterers,</l>
                  <l>Which into Princes ears gently diſtill</l>
                  <l>The poiſon of theſe maxims, as if human</l>
                  <l>Nature could thus comply with ſervitude,</l>
                  <l>Not foaming at the Curb; Sir, like ſea waves,</l>
                  <l>Impetuouſly forc'd by ſeveral winds,</l>
                  <l>We are by the tempeſtuous torrents hurri'd</l>
                  <l>Of rage, ambition, choller, and revenge:</l>
                  <l>Of which the latter juſtly has provokt</l>
                  <l>My indignation againſt <hi>Valentius.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Nothing can juſtifie theſe practiſes</l>
                  <l>Againſt your Prince.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arſ.</speaker>
                  <l>But to the ſubject, to return from which</l>
                  <l>We deviate now; I have of late obtain'd</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aurelia</hi> by the conſent of her Father</l>
                  <l>In marriage for my Son, to whom I lately</l>
                  <l>Addreſt a letter ſignifying the ſame,</l>
                  <stage>ſhews him a letter.</stage>
                  <l>Intending you the happy bearer of</l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:59228:11"/>
                  <l>This grateful news, of which another Copy</l>
                  <l>I to <hi>Aurelia</hi> ſent, to ſhew my pen</l>
                  <l>As forward as my ſword in the procuring</l>
                  <l>Hers, and her Fathers intereſt; but ſince</l>
                  <l>Conſidering in deſperate diſeaſes,</l>
                  <l>That extreme remedies are beſt, I've chang'd</l>
                  <l>My thoughts, perſwaded that a Fathers preſence</l>
                  <l>Will be more prevalent</l>
                  <l>Then the mute eloquence of Paper; ſo</l>
                  <l>Behold me here arrived, to procure</l>
                  <l>An end to my calamities; my Sons</l>
                  <l>Greateſt felicity; the ruine of</l>
                  <l>The perſecutor of my life, <hi>Valentius.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Give o're this raſh diſcourſe; here thou ſhouldſt die</l>
                  <l>The ſacrifice of my juſt indignation,</l>
                  <stage>draws at him.</stage>
                  <l>Wer't not to envy thy brave Sons ſecure</l>
                  <l>Triumphing over thy vain ſtratagems.</l>
                  <l>Doſt hope through my protection to put</l>
                  <l>Thy treacherous practice into execution</l>
                  <l>Againſt my Prince? the ſound of this diſcourſe</l>
                  <l>More odious is to me then the noiſe</l>
                  <l>Of chains or fetters, which I'le rather ſuffer.</l>
                  <l>Theſe abject thoughts proportionate, and proper</l>
                  <l>Are to thy doating age; attribute to</l>
                  <l>Thy fortune of having ſo brave a Son</l>
                  <stage>puts up his ſword.</stage>
                  <l>The life, thou receiv'ſt from theſe generous hands.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <l>Is it a generous part thus to reward</l>
                  <l>My benefit with this ingratitude?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>A benefit conferred in the ſenſe</l>
                  <l>Of intereſt, merits no recompence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <l>My forward love miſtaken was to try</l>
                  <l>To gain affection from an Enemy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy hopes are vain, it was thy error here</l>
                  <l>With curteſie to 'abuſe a Gentleman.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <l>A Gentleman, who ſuch reſentment ſhows</l>
                  <l>The man, to whom his liberty he owes?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Can he be author of my liberty,</l>
                  <l>Who would engage me in this treacherie?</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:59228:12"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, is it treacherouſly, or nobly done,</l>
                  <l>To reconcile a Father to a Son?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>A Father, he who ſeeks to rob a Son</l>
                  <l>Of his true honor, and reputation?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <l>Honor to ſpend his youth, and time, and die</l>
                  <l>In ſervice of his Fathers Enemy?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>His reſpect to his Father muſt give way</l>
                  <l>To that of his true Prince, who all muſt ſway.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <l>Mans firſt, and greateſt duty from the tye</l>
                  <l>Of nature comes, not human policy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Nature muſt yield to reaſon, which thinks fit,</l>
                  <l>Privat to publick int'reſt ſhould ſubmit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <l>Go to thy Son <hi>Arſenius,</hi> and try,</l>
                  <l>If he be cruel like thy Enemy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Go to thy Son <hi>Arſenius;</hi> there's his Tent:</l>
                  <l>A Fathers ignominy there lament;</l>
                  <stage>points to the Tents of the Camp.</stage>
                  <l>And a Sons glory, as thy puniſhment.</l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <head>ACT. II.</head>
               <stage>Fulvia, Antonia. Attendants.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>ALl but <hi>Antonia</hi> leave the place.</l>
                  <l>Exceſſive griefs, <hi>Antonia,</hi> receive</l>
                  <l>No mitigation from advice of friends:</l>
                  <l>And ſuch are mine; ſo that if I implore</l>
                  <l>Aſſiſtance, I exaſperate them more.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, what cauſes this ſtrange alteration?</l>
                  <l>So many nights your eyes have ſeen no ſleep,</l>
                  <l>Which chang'd of late, have loſt their uſual luſtre.</l>
                  <l>Your looks and ſpeech are not accompany'd</l>
                  <l>With their accuſtom'd graces; as ſome ſick</l>
                  <l>Perſons, in cold languiſhing all the night,</l>
                  <l>With feavors burning at th' approach of light;</l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:59228:12"/>
                  <l>Juſt ſo your Majeſty the Sun offends</l>
                  <l>When he his courſe begins, or when he ends.</l>
                  <l>Th' arrival of the night gives you no eaſe;</l>
                  <l>That of the day your torments does increaſe.</l>
                  <l>To me your ſervant why d'you thus affect</l>
                  <l>To hide the cauſe, who tell you the effect?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſhall I do? confeſſions of our crimes</l>
                  <l>In Princes are worſe crimes then they themſelves;</l>
                  <l>And which, if I ſtrive longer to conceal,</l>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <l>This forced ſilence will at laſt reveal:</l>
                  <l>—Let then my will,</l>
                  <l>Which in an Empreſs ſhould be ſole Commander,</l>
                  <l>The voluntary firſt eruption make.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Antonia,</hi> thou ſhalt now know my diſeaſe,</l>
                  <l>But let compaſſion mollifie thy heart</l>
                  <l>Conformable to the grief, which I ſuffer.</l>
                  <l>Who the diſtreſs'd relieve, muſt firſt reſent,</l>
                  <l>And feel the torment of the Patient.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Florus,</hi> that name ſo grateful to <hi>Antonia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But more to me.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Florus,</hi> I ſay to thee, ſo acceptable.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>—Madam, 'tis true, 'twas he</l>
                  <l>Who firſt to my <hi>Servilius</hi> me united.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>—And me has diſunited from my ſelf,</l>
                  <l>My Prince, the world, and all things but himſelf.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Florus</hi> more fair, more beautiful than is</l>
                  <l>Morning or midnight ſtar, more lovely then</l>
                  <l>The pleaſant Sun himſelf, when he ſhines through</l>
                  <l>The golden Fleece of the coeleſtial Ram.</l>
                  <l>—O how I am,</l>
                  <l>With love tranſported.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>True;</l>
                  <l>But 'tis, I hope, of your <hi>Valentius.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>No; 'tis not: yes, it is; I mean of him:</l>
                  <l>Not what he is, but what he was; in <hi>Florus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Me thinks I ſee <hi>Valentius</hi> reviv'd,</l>
                  <l>And my old flames: Love has</l>
                  <l>Retrac'd the ſame imaginations in</l>
                  <l>My fancy, which kindled my firſt deſires.</l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:59228:13"/>
                  <l>Nature gave the ſame features to their faces,</l>
                  <l>And to their minds and bodies the ſame graces.</l>
                  <l>Such ſprightlineſs was in <hi>Valentius</hi> looks,</l>
                  <l>When firſt he courted me:</l>
                  <l>Such was his comely geſture, when on horſeback</l>
                  <l>The ſtately courſer proud was of his burden.</l>
                  <l>Thus ſmil'd he, thus he frown'd, and in his anger</l>
                  <l>Became more lovely from the change of paſſions.</l>
                  <l>Marvel not then, that ſo great a Commander</l>
                  <l>So ſoon has conquer'd, and inflam'd the breaſt,</l>
                  <l>Alas! of a poor Lady.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe heats ſhould be ſuppreſt in their beginning.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>And ſo they might; did they like other fires</l>
                  <l>Grow by ſucceſſion; but they maſterleſs</l>
                  <l>Like lightning, found expanſion in an inſtant</l>
                  <l>Through all my veins, inflaming all my ſpirits.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>Caſt off theſe vain ſurmiſes, and be ſure</l>
                  <l>the thought you may be cur'd, is half the cure.</l>
                  <l>Let not your Majeſty herein perſever,</l>
                  <l>We ſafely ſin ſometimes, ſecurely never.</l>
                  <l>Strangle theſe vile thoughts in their infancy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>This I have oft endeavour'd, but in vain</l>
                  <l>—So whilſt that I</l>
                  <l>Am thus conſum'd by an internal fire,</l>
                  <l>Scarce daring to let it evaporate</l>
                  <l>In words, in ſighs, in tears like other lovers;</l>
                  <l>The heat increaſing, multiplies within</l>
                  <l>My breaſt, and will, I fear, at laſt for want</l>
                  <l>Of vent deſtroy me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, theſe thoughts ſhould have no vent, but find</l>
                  <l>At once their birth, and burial in your mind.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>My vital heat, and this more vital of</l>
                  <l>My love, are ſubſtances inſeparable;</l>
                  <l>Nay, if the nature of my ſoul ſhall not prove</l>
                  <l>Mortal, I fear that will not of my love:</l>
                  <l>So that to ſave my honor if I die,</l>
                  <l>I am not ſure to end my miſerie.</l>
                  <l>Wilt thou not then afford me thy compaſſion?</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:59228:13"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>To her who voluntary caſts her ſelf</l>
                  <l>In miſerie, what pity can be due?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>O 'tis againſt my will; love like a Tyrant has</l>
                  <l>Reduc't my ſoul, and all her faculties</l>
                  <l>In vaſſalage: Virtue lets fall her arms,</l>
                  <l>As weak, and uſeleſs, 'againſt ſuch pow'rful charms.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <p>Think on the violation of your faith.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>I have, and find, that conſtancy is only</l>
                  <l>A force imaginary in us women:</l>
                  <l>I find it by my ſelf.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <p>But not by others.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <p>Canſt ſee me periſh, and afford no ſuccour?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>Want of aſſiſtance in this kind preſerves you.</l>
                  <l>My ſuccor in this caſe would make you periſh.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy Empreſs ſubmiſſively intreats,</l>
                  <l>And wilt thou not obey?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>learn to command,</l>
                  <l>And firſt your ſelf, and then I ſhall obey.</l>
                  <l>I am your ſervant, not ſlave of your vice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <p>Canſt thou a Lover be, and yet ſo cruel?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <p>My love I keep confin'd within due limits.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>Contrivers of crimes ſecretly committed</l>
                  <l>In Courts, ſecurely ſtill advance themſelves,</l>
                  <l>Without the loſs of fame, or reputation.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>We doubly erre; if erring we procure</l>
                  <l>Th' opinion, that we have conſerv'd our honor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>—If we approve in Princes</l>
                  <l>Actions unjuſt for private int'reſt, why not</l>
                  <l>Thoſe more excuſable for private pleaſure?</l>
                  <l>A hidden fault was never entire crime.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <p>That which is voluntary, is entire.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>But not in Princes, who being publick perſons,</l>
                  <l>Their vices, if not publick, are not vices;</l>
                  <l>Nor private virtues eſteem'd Princely virtues.</l>
                  <l>'Tis cruelty not to aſſiſt th' afflicted.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <p>Not when contrivers of their own misfortunes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <p>O thou art obſtinat.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis conſtancy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis cruelty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis generoſity.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <p>Ingratitude in the moſt high degree.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <p>Greateſt beneficence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <p>Thy Princes hater.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:59228:14"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <p>A lover of her honor, and my own.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <p>No more <hi>Antonia:</hi> ſhall I live, or die?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <p>Then loſs of honor, death's leſs miſerie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſhall I do? my reaſon having loſt,</l>
                  <l>Whiles fury guides me, I rove ſtrangely toſt,</l>
                  <l>I know not where, but certainly aſtray,</l>
                  <l>Where honor ſuffers mad love to lead the way.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Arſenius. Honorius. Florus putting up his ſword.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>No, no; I can't believe it; 'tis almoſt</l>
                  <l>Impoſſible, that he ſhould be my Father,</l>
                  <l>Who ſeeks thus to deprive me of my honor,</l>
                  <l>In forfeiting my duty to my Prince.</l>
                  <l>—Acknowledge in pure gift</l>
                  <l>Thy life from my unlucky ignorance</l>
                  <l>Of him, who is my Father.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Brave <hi>Florus,</hi> this new field maintain,</l>
                  <l>Which virtue has laid open with intention</l>
                  <l>To ſignalize thy valor in all kinds.</l>
                  <l>Nature her ſelf thou here ſubdueſt, not words</l>
                  <l>Of human art or hand; and which is moſt,</l>
                  <l>None in this conqueſt, but thy ſelf can boaſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <p>My Son.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fl.</speaker>
                  <p>My Enemy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <p>My only Son.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <p>My greateſt Enemy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou know'ſt I ſeek</l>
                  <l>Thy happineſs, and canſt thou injure me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>Is this an injury, to defend my ſelf</l>
                  <l>From th'undermining practice of a Traytor?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <l>Canſt thou ſubmit to ſerve a Prince, who is</l>
                  <l>An enemy to him, who gave thee being.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>Suppoſe you did, will you on this account</l>
                  <l>Rob me of my well-being, fame, and honor?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <l>Diſguiſ'd here in theſe abject weeds, for thee</l>
                  <l>My grandour, and my dignity, and life</l>
                  <l>To hazard I expoſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>Return; thou haſt free leave, and reaſſume</l>
                  <l>Thy Generalſhip under <hi>Hoſtilius:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It is my glory in the head of armies</l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:59228:14"/>
                  <l>To meet me as my adverſary; but</l>
                  <l>My ſhame, diſgrace, and ignominy to</l>
                  <l>Reſpect thee with the reverence of a Father.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <l>Cruel Barbarian, if thou diſpiſeſt</l>
                  <l>Thy Father, from whom thou enjoy'ſt this light;</l>
                  <l>At leaſt make ſome account of him, who ſeeks</l>
                  <l>To put thee in poſſeſſion of that</l>
                  <l>Thou lov'ſt above this light, thy fair <hi>Aurelia.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>When my affection to <hi>Aurelia</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall be offenſive to <hi>Valentius,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ile caſt it off.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <p>Art thou reſolv'd to refuſe me all pity?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhall obſerve my duty to my Prince.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <l>Which ſhould give place to thy paternal duty,</l>
                  <l>And is ingrafted in all breſts but thine;</l>
                  <l>—Known long before,</l>
                  <l>Private ambition, popular faction</l>
                  <l>Had laid the ruines, or the foundations</l>
                  <l>Of Principalities, or Commonwealths,</l>
                  <l>Whence theſe names ſprang of loyalty, and honor.</l>
                  <l>The cruel Thracian, barbarous Indian</l>
                  <l>Acknowledging no other law, know this:</l>
                  <l>So does th' inhoſpitable Scythian,</l>
                  <l>Who others bloud devouring, with his own</l>
                  <l>His aged fainting <hi>Sire</hi> will revive.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>—My cruel fortune!</l>
                  <l>When thy looks faireſt are, how thou confound'ſt me?</l>
                  <l>Here filial obligation, which nature</l>
                  <l>Imprints not only in mens hearts, but beaſts,</l>
                  <l>Challenges my obedience to a Father;</l>
                  <l>Who not content to give me life, ſeeks here</l>
                  <l>With hazard of his own, to make mine happy.</l>
                  <l>On th' other ſide my Prince, who has prevented</l>
                  <l>My age, my merit, and my expectation,</l>
                  <l>With heaping on me honors upon honors,</l>
                  <l>Exacts more from me then my gratitude</l>
                  <l>Equaliz'd to my wiſhes could repay.</l>
                  <l>O how thus ſtrangely circumvented I</l>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:59228:15"/>
                  <l>Far greater torment find to live then die!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Florus,</hi> why thus perplext? what in a dream?</l>
                  <l>Diſpel theſe cloudy miſts, follow the way,</l>
                  <l>Where honor lights thee with her golden ray.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Honorius,</hi> thou haſt turn'd the balance, which</l>
                  <l>My trembling heart durſt neither way incline.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <l>Unfortunate <hi>Arſenius!</hi> what new hopes</l>
                  <l>Canſt thou retain, when they ingrateful are,</l>
                  <l>Which have ſuch benefits receiv'd from thee;</l>
                  <l>The one is life, the other liberty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>T'oblige the innocent, to make him guilty.</l>
                  <l>Is not a benefit, but treachery.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <l>Ah <hi>Florus,</hi> ſome reſpect to theſe gray hairs,</l>
                  <l>My Son, ſome duty's due to me, thy Father.</l>
                  <l>Let theſe my tears mollifie that hard heart,</l>
                  <l>Which ſo inflexible ſeems to my prayers.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>—Old man give over;</l>
                  <l>Thy words, and time are loſt in this purſuit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <l>—Raſh and inhuman creature,</l>
                  <l>If thou diſpiſeſt the entreaties of a Father:</l>
                  <l>—Ile make thee fear the courage,</l>
                  <l>And ſtratagems of an old General</l>
                  <l>Grown white under the helmot, and the rage</l>
                  <l>Of an incenſed Enemy: <hi>Valentius</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall know <hi>Aurelia</hi>'s thy intended Spouſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hoſtilius</hi> thy private Friend: ſo ſhall</l>
                  <l>This artifice at once deprive thee of</l>
                  <l>Thy honor, and of that unworthy being,</l>
                  <l>Which I unworthily have given thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>O nature, O my honor, cruel Tyrants</l>
                  <l>Of my divided ſoul, how you diſtract me!</l>
                  <l>In what inextricable labyrinth</l>
                  <l>Has my ill fortune caſt me? if I conquer,</l>
                  <l>Or yield ſubdu'd in this unhappy conflict</l>
                  <l>Of my conteſting paſſions, and affections,</l>
                  <l>I'm ſure to loſe my life, or reputation;</l>
                  <l>Or rather both, which my ſad thoughts preſage.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Fear nothing; be not thus dejected, whilſt</l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:59228:15"/>
                  <l>Here's an <hi>Honorius</hi> to give ſo ample</l>
                  <l>A teſtimony of your innocence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>Malicious dotard, do thy worſt, my clear</l>
                  <l>Sincerity of mind, and actions ſhall</l>
                  <l>Prove, thou a Traytor canſt not be my Father.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Arſenius,</hi> thou ſpend'ſt thy time, thy words,</l>
                  <l>And labor here in vain: come then prepare</l>
                  <l>For thy revenge.</l>
                  <l>The world ſhall know what I thought to conceal.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>—<hi>Arſenius</hi> hold:</l>
                  <l>Ah ſtay, and lets compoſe this cruel ſtrife;</l>
                  <l>You pretend only to have giv'n me life,</l>
                  <l>Which I'le return t' you: opening thus my breſt,</l>
                  <l>The paſſage will make entrance for my reſt;</l>
                  <l>The bloud will be the balſom of my honor,</l>
                  <l>And pay your debt, and ſave my reputation.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Arſenius,</hi> O thy unhappy fortune!</l>
                  <l>Which made thee Father, Souldier, or Commander!</l>
                  <l>Live cruel Parricide, live, and prolong</l>
                  <l>Thy odious life; I'le find ſome way to death,</l>
                  <l>And my repoſe: my ſelf I cannot ſhew</l>
                  <l>A cruel Father, or ſoft-natur'd Foe.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Florus,</hi> why thus caſt down? 'tis ſtrange to ſee</l>
                  <l>A man dejected after victory.</l>
                  <l>Here nothing was requir'd but a ſpectator</l>
                  <l>Of this moſt glorious paſſage of thy life,</l>
                  <l>Which the propitious aſpect of the heavens</l>
                  <l>Has granted thee in an <hi>Honorius.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Florus</hi> farewel; congratulate thy happy</l>
                  <l>Fortune to have preſerv'd a Friend, who ſeeks</l>
                  <l>The preſervation of thy honor; which</l>
                  <l>Thy Father, thou here loſeſt, ſought to ruine.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>There is no reaſon nature ſhould unite</l>
                  <l>By an uſurp'd authority thoſe minds,</l>
                  <l>Virtue upon juſt grounds has ſeparated.</l>
                  <l>But ſee th' Empreſs comes: I'm ſorry ſhe</l>
                  <l>Should find me in this conflict of my paſſions.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:59228:16"/>
               <stage>Fulvia. Florus.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>Ladies retire within; I will be private.</l>
                  <l>See here in finding <hi>Florus</hi> alone, a happy</l>
                  <l>Occaſion is preſented by my fortune</l>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <l>For the diſcovery of my paſſion (which</l>
                  <l>As womens wits are beſt when they have leaſt</l>
                  <l>Time to conſider) I have found already.</l>
                  <l>I'le tell him that I hear his love aſpires</l>
                  <l>To the poſſeſſion of a Royal Lady,</l>
                  <l>Who meets his flames with mutual fire, commending</l>
                  <l>Herein his choice; ſo by this artifice</l>
                  <l>He ſhall perceive my love in a ſurprize.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Florus,</hi> what is th' occaſion of this ſadneſs,</l>
                  <l>VVhen th'Emperour ſo much applauds your conduct?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, to ſee the enemy provide</l>
                  <l>Againſt us a more vigorous aſſault.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis but a new occaſion for your triumph.</l>
                  <l>I know the real cauſe of this diſturbance.</l>
                  <l>O <hi>Florus</hi> you aſpire to great matters.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Servilius</hi> or my Father has betray'd me.</p>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay I commend your courſe, 'twas virtue which</l>
                  <l>Diſtinguiſht, and made Princes-firſt; beſides</l>
                  <l>Love's a great leveller like death, and where</l>
                  <l>He finds not an equality, will make it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>—I ſhall be of the Court</l>
                  <l>Now, and the Camp the laughing-ſtock and ſport.</l>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>If you deſir'd ſuch ſecreſie, you ſhould not</l>
                  <l>Make one the object of your love, ſo near</l>
                  <l>In bloud to me allied.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aurelia</hi> is her Niece; 'tis very true:</l>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <l>If I perſiſt, this ſilence will convince me.</l>
                  <l>Let not your ſacred Majeſty be thus</l>
                  <l>Abuſ'd by falſe reports; my Princes favor</l>
                  <l>And yours (as ever happens in great Courts)</l>
                  <l>Have raiſ'd me private enemies, which ſeek</l>
                  <l>My ruin from theſe falſe ſuggeſtions.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:59228:16"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>No, no; here's no place for the leaſt ſuſpicion</l>
                  <l>Againſt the teſtimony of this truth,</l>
                  <l>Which from the Ladies lips proceeds, who loves you;</l>
                  <l>Which here this Medal better will declare</l>
                  <stage>gives him a Medal.</stage>
                  <l>Then words, which through reſpect of you, and of</l>
                  <l>My ſelf I cannot utter.</l>
                  <l>Confront this with th' orignal, and ſee</l>
                  <l>If ſhe be well expreſt, who thus affects you.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Plo.</speaker>
                  <l>Let's ſee if the Inſcription ſhew the ſame</l>
                  <l>Perſon, the picture ſeems to repreſent.</l>
                  <stage>turns about the Medal.</stage>
                  <stage>Fulvia Empreſs, ſecond Wife of Valentius, &amp;c.</stage>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Is this ſome real paſſage, or illuſion?</l>
                     <l>Perchance I dream, and now ſome lively viſions</l>
                     <l>Play the Impoſtors on my deluded fancy.</l>
                     <l>I wiſh it were ſo; but that ſcarce can be;</l>
                     <l>For though in dreams we think our ſelves awake,</l>
                     <l>Yet really awake we know we dream not.</l>
                     <l>No, I am the loſt miſerable <hi>Florus;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And this the cruel <hi>Fulvia,</hi> who deſtroys me;</l>
                     <l>And which is ſtrange, with love; a ſtronger engine</l>
                     <l>Erected for my ruine, then her hatred.</l>
                     <l>Who can eſteem me innocent? whilſt I</l>
                     <l>Am flexible thought to ſo foul a crime.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Blaſt me ye heavens, or elſe at leaſt theſe looks,</l>
                     <l>Which pleaſe the Empreſs: if my heart be chaſt,</l>
                     <l>They are laſcivious, and my honor ſtain:</l>
                     <l>And this ſufficient is to make me guilty.</l>
                     <l>Was ever caſe like mine! If I declare</l>
                     <l>My ſelf a lover then I loſe my friends;</l>
                     <l>And if I am belov'd, my Prince I injure</l>
                     <l>In higheſt point of honor, and what's ſtrange,</l>
                     <l>Th'offendor is in both wayes innocent.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antonia.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>'Tis ſtrange my Huſbands love ſhould fade ſo ſoon,</l>
                     <l>Which I have ſought to cultivate with all</l>
                     <l>Art, duty, offices which can become</l>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:59228:17"/>
                     <l>A ſubtle woman, or complacent wife.</l>
                     <l>Perchance I am deceiv'd, and with ſome falſe</l>
                     <l>Surmiſe create within my ſelf true torment.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O Geloſie; o thou quickſighted daughter</l>
                     <l>Of thy blind father Love, of whom at laſt</l>
                     <l>Thou prov'ſt the murd'rer: thou of all things only</l>
                     <l>Deteſted, loathed, hated by thy ſelf;</l>
                     <l>Ingenious only in the ſearching after</l>
                     <l>That, which thou wiſheſt could not be found out;</l>
                     <l>Or being found, leaves thee in greater torment.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Since in ſo ſhort a time thy venom has</l>
                     <l>Spread through my veins, and poiſon'd all my thoughts;</l>
                     <l>Return to thy infernal manſion, where</l>
                     <l>Hatred begot thee, though perchance ſome ſhare</l>
                     <l>Love in thy generation might have,</l>
                     <l>To make thy birth double, and ſo more monſtrous:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>There be a torment to thy ſelf, and ſince</l>
                     <l>Suſpicions are thy choiceſt nouriſhment.</l>
                     <l>Vex thy ſelf with new fears; never ſecure,</l>
                     <l>As well with thoſe which doubtful are, as ſure.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>To her</hi> Servilius.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>Here comes my poor <hi>Antonia,</hi> methinks,</l>
                  <l>The ſad reproach of my inconſtancy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>What cauſe have I giv'n you of late to be</l>
                  <l>So much diſguſted with my company?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>None, but ſome other flames have in my breſt</l>
                  <l>Extinguiſht thine, and rob me of my reſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>What can theſe ſtrange looks, or this language mean?</l>
                  <l>I hope Sir, you intend no breach of faith.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>No, I am forc'd to it againſt my intention.</l>
                  <l>Againſt my former vows, and my own wiſhes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>We all confeſs, Sir, this unqueſtion'd truth,</l>
                  <l>Mans will cannot be forc't, though it rebel,</l>
                  <l>By any power on earth, in heaven, or hell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>If here's an error, <hi>Florus</hi> ſhould be rather</l>
                  <l>Accuſ'd then I: he, who firſt joyn'd our loves.</l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:59228:17"/>
                  <l>Has been the occaſion of diſſolving them,</l>
                  <l>In ſhewing me a face of late in beauty</l>
                  <l>So far tranſcending thine,</l>
                  <l>That 'twere impiety not to adore it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>—Falſe and diſloyal man;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Florus</hi> and thou ſhalt ſink under the force</l>
                  <l>Of my revenge, provok't to ſuch a height,</l>
                  <l>It ſhall pluck on you both untimely fate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Antonia,</hi> divert the torrent of</l>
                  <l>This furious rage ſome other way; accuſe</l>
                  <l>Nature, who has to my exceſſive torment</l>
                  <l>This beauty form'd, ſo far excelling thine,</l>
                  <l>As the moon does the leſſer ſtars out-ſhine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>Traytor accuſe thy one perfidiouſneſs,</l>
                  <l>Which makes thee change thy promiſe, and thy cuſtoms.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>I have chang'd the object only, not my cuſtom.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>Th' haſt broke thy faith; this makes thee infamous.</l>
                  <l>I hope in her thou followſt, thou wilt ſee</l>
                  <l>An hatred equal to my love of thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Antonia</hi> examining thy glaſs</l>
                  <l>Accuſe that vulgar beauty, and thy face,</l>
                  <l>Which on my free-born ſoul has had no charms</l>
                  <l>More pow'rful, and ſuch early fading colours.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>—Go; go;</l>
                     <l>Go, if my beauty be of untimely fate,</l>
                     <l>In my revenge ſo ſhall not be my hate;</l>
                     <l>To perfect which, I heaven, and hel will move:</l>
                     <l>'Tis th' only recompence, of injur'd love.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nature, and Fortune cruel Stepmothers</l>
                     <l>Are to us women: in our tender years</l>
                     <l>Our Fathers Palaces to us are Priſons,</l>
                     <l>Where nor our perſons, nor ſcarce our looks are free:</l>
                     <l>And afterward, when our maturity</l>
                     <l>Should change this bondage into liberty;</l>
                     <l>We only of all creatures are who buy</l>
                     <l>With a vaſt dowry our own ſlavery:</l>
                     <l>Thus only changing a new Maſter, whom</l>
                     <l>We purchaſe to rule o'r our ſouls and bodies,</l>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:59228:18"/>
                     <l>And caſt us off thus when he pleaſe. Man is</l>
                     <l>A bold inſolent creature; grand uſurper</l>
                     <l>Upon the rights of nature; not by his wit</l>
                     <l>(For in our age of folly we enſlave him)</l>
                     <l>But by his force, and number. He makes lawes</l>
                     <l>Partial t' himſelf, rigid to us: his vows</l>
                     <l>He breaks, ours muſt be kept; his vices</l>
                     <l>Paſs only for his gallantries; ours are</l>
                     <l>Branded with foul and horrid names t' affright us.</l>
                     <l>Ambition in us, in him is honor;</l>
                     <l>And our irregular appetites in him</l>
                     <l>Paſs for the noble paſſions of his love;</l>
                     <l>Not only to be excuſ'd, but commended.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Who made theſe laws and cuſtoms? did our Sex</l>
                     <l>Ever give up their voice, and ſuffrages?</l>
                     <l>No: there's no right, or obligation then</l>
                     <l>We ſhould obey theſe orders made by men,</l>
                     <l>So partial Judges: th' Empreſs and I will ſee</l>
                     <l>To vindicate our ſexes libertie.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <head>ACT. III.</head>
               <stage>Florus. Servilius. Carbo.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>That which you tell us, is a ſecret of</l>
                  <l>Importance, that <hi>Arſenius</hi> ſhould be</l>
                  <l>Your Father, and converſe here in our Camp.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis True; but I am now relating to you</l>
                  <l>Th' occaſion which has brought <hi>Aurelia</hi> hither.</l>
                  <l>The wild luſt of her Father, not content</l>
                  <l>To violate the chaſtity of Virgins,</l>
                  <l>The faith of Matrons, Widows vows; at laſt</l>
                  <l>Laſciviouſly incroached on his Daughter:</l>
                  <l>The horror of which thought ſo frighted her</l>
                  <l>(Such was her vertuous innocence) ſhe ſought</l>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:59228:18"/>
                  <l>Her refuge from her enemies, and fled</l>
                  <l>From him her Father, as her greateſt foe.</l>
                  <l>So by this means fortune affords my arms</l>
                  <l>Th' happy occaſion of protecting virtue,</l>
                  <l>I think her ſelf in a corporeal ſhape.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>This paſſion of your love ſtrangely deceives you.</l>
                  <l>Virtue needs no external form, or beauty</l>
                  <l>Seldom puts any on; and yet more ſeldom</l>
                  <l>'Tis that they can agree.</l>
                  <l>Chiefly in Courts, like jarring Elements,</l>
                  <l>Where one proves the confuſion of the other;</l>
                  <l>Beauty at leaſt to Virtue ever fatal.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>He tells you true, the outward ſhape of your</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aurelia</hi> ſhews no internal goodneſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>—Sure correſpondent to</l>
                  <l>Th' external ſplendor muſt be lodg'd in her</l>
                  <l>A ſoul deſerving ſuch an habitation;</l>
                  <l>As greater luſtre of ſome ſparkling jewels</l>
                  <l>Denotes in them no leſs intrinſique virtue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I can compare <hi>Aurelia's</hi> eyes to ſtars</l>
                  <l>As bright as you, but of ill influence,</l>
                  <l>And look on her arrival to the Camp,</l>
                  <l>Like the approach of ſome ill threatning Comet.</l>
                  <l>Th' heavens preſerve our General, and us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>What raiſes theſe ſtrange Omens of my love,</l>
                  <l>Which ſome will envy, but the moſt approve.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>Moſt will condemn, others oppoſe; think not</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aurelia</hi>'s beauty will not raiſe you Rivals,</l>
                  <l>To bring the Prize in conteſtation.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>Theſe motives of vain fear I ſcorn; farewel,</l>
                  <l>I'le ſeek ſome other friends to gratulate</l>
                  <l>The happineſs of my triumphing fate.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I am amaz'd to think <hi>Arſenius,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Great Captain General of our enemy,</l>
                  <l>Should be his Father; and here in diſguiſe</l>
                  <l>Converſe within our Camp.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis a ſtrange ſecret.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>To me it ſeems improbable, that he</l>
                  <l>Who was ſurpriz'd with the meer ſhadow of</l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:59228:19"/>
                  <l>His Miſtreſs, ſhould remain inflexible</l>
                  <l>To the tears and entreaties of a Father:</l>
                  <l>What's your opinion?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>That we play the fool</l>
                  <l>Egregiouſly; remember we are Souldiers</l>
                  <l>As well as Courtiers; lets caſt off this diſſembling.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Since you advance, I'le meet you: Sir I hear</l>
                  <l>Of your intention of divorce, to make</l>
                  <l>Room for <hi>Aurelia</hi>'s entrance in your bed;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe love I ſeek with as great fervency</l>
                  <l>As you; we both forfeit our hopes, if this</l>
                  <l>Rival be not remov'd; th'effecting which</l>
                  <l>His open folly has made eaſie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>True;</l>
                     <l>As Scholars prove ill Souldiers, ſo theſe Souldiers</l>
                     <l>Prove the worſt Courtiers; their franc and gen'rous natures</l>
                     <l>Make them as unfit for the air of Courts,</l>
                     <l>As birds are for the Element of water.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Who but a General bred up in Camps</l>
                     <l>Like <hi>Florus,</hi> ſuch a ſecret would reveal,</l>
                     <l>On which divulg'd, his ruin does depend,</l>
                     <l>To us, who ſhall raiſe our ſelves from his fall.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>In Court it would a Soloeciſm appear,</l>
                  <l>So groſs an error ſhould unpuniſht go:</l>
                  <l>There is no reaſon for't, he muſt give way,</l>
                  <l>Though both of us can't have this glorious prey:</l>
                  <l>And conſequently in our Gen'rals fall,</l>
                  <l>The one of us muſt find his Funeral.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Valentius, Statilius, Honorius, with Court-Attendants, &amp;c.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Statilius,</hi> the Gods are equally</l>
                  <l>Willing to make us great, as afterwards</l>
                  <l>They are averſe long to conſerve that greatneſs.</l>
                  <l>We often ſee our fall, or miſerie</l>
                  <l>Bring up the rear of our proſperitie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Majeſty knows well that our condition</l>
                  <l>Admits not of a ſincere happineſs,</l>
                  <l>Without the mixture of ſome diſcontent.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Whilſt <hi>Italy</hi> and the Provinces applaud.</l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:59228:19"/>
                  <l>My victories, and happineſs, I fear,</l>
                  <l>And yet perceive no true cauſe of my fear.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis generouſly to be rejected then,</l>
                  <l>As being grounded upon no foundation.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Thence it takes deeper root. Old Mariners</l>
                  <l>Expect a horrid tempeſt, when the ſea</l>
                  <l>Rouls boyſtrous waves, and yet no winds are ſtirring.</l>
                  <l>Laſt night, or rather 'twixt the confines of</l>
                  <l>The day and night, the lively, but the diſmal</l>
                  <l>Impreſſions of a dream have ſo tormented</l>
                  <l>My ſpirit, I ſhall have no quiet till</l>
                  <l>I ſee the menacing effects blown over.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Theſe are deceptions of the fancy, not</l>
                  <l>Deſerving the attention of a Prince.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>So often verifi'd in all reports,</l>
                  <l>Who can aſſure us theſe are fallacies?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>The rare, divine, admired <hi>Epicurus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who with the light of reaſon has diſpel'd</l>
                  <l>Theſe golden fears, theſe terrifiers of</l>
                  <l>The vulgar ſpirits; did you but imagine</l>
                  <l>Th' innumerable multitude of ſuch</l>
                  <l>Who either will deceive, or be deceiv'd:</l>
                  <l>Nothing ſo beneficial you'l ſee</l>
                  <l>As a judicious incredulitie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis a ſigne of a poor and mollifi'd</l>
                  <l>Spirit to fear all events of this nature;</l>
                  <l>And to fear nothing a ſtupiditie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>A virtue Sir, if once opinion can</l>
                  <l>Remove us from our ſolid ſtation,</l>
                  <l>We never after ſhall firm footing find.</l>
                  <l>An underſtanding muſt be, to ſee clear,</l>
                  <l>Purg'd from all ſuperſtition and fear.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>It is an happineſs to be reſolute</l>
                  <l>In our opinions, though erroneous.</l>
                  <l>O that I could like thee, <hi>Honorius,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Believe theſe terrors follies: my dream was,</l>
                  <l>That my dear Wife, and eldeſt Son; O horror!</l>
                  <l>Before we ſee the Sun once more aſcend</l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:59228:20"/>
                  <l>To his meridian altitude, ſhould fall</l>
                  <l>At my feet murder'd by me in furious rage.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <l>The vanity herein appears, that in</l>
                  <l>The ſhort extent of one dayes compaſs ſo</l>
                  <l>Horrid a fact muſt be accompliſht, which</l>
                  <l>Requireth years for the maturing of it.</l>
                  <l>The innocence and virtue of the Empreſs,</l>
                  <l>And Prince are yet unblemiſht, inſuſpected.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis true; but if the fates will make <hi>Valentius</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Unhappy, they will make him firſt imprudent.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>The happineſs of great <hi>Valentius</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Depends upon the will of great <hi>Valentius:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Not upon, fortune, or deſtiny.</l>
                  <l>Theſe are but idle names of idle Writers,</l>
                  <l>—Unhappily invented,</l>
                  <l>To terrifie mankind, and ſow the ſeeds</l>
                  <l>Of error, folly, ſuperſtition in us:</l>
                  <l>Who ſhould rely on our own proper virtues;</l>
                  <l>For man is only on himſelf dependant;</l>
                  <l>Not fate, nor fortune, nor his ſtars Aſcendant.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Thinkſt thou not ſome celeſtial pow'rs above</l>
                  <l>Direct the courſe of our affairs?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>No Sir</l>
                  <l>They reſt ſecure, happy not thinking on them,</l>
                  <l>Nor us, ſuch little crawlers here on earth.</l>
                  <l>Nor is it human wit, but rather human</l>
                  <l>Folly, which now ſeems the diſpoſer of them.</l>
                  <l>Obſerve but with what vermin the age ſwarms,</l>
                  <l>And how the world is ſtrangely people with</l>
                  <l>Armies of murderers in ambitious wars;</l>
                  <l>Or elſe the inſtruments of our luxury.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>I am told by my Philoſophers at Court,</l>
                  <l>Confuſ'd, and interrupted dreams are not</l>
                  <l>To be regarded; but when that order is</l>
                  <l>In them which was in mine, they are adviſes</l>
                  <l>From heaven ſent to tell us what ſhall happen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>—In the diſtracted Chaos</l>
                  <l>There never was greater confuſion,</l>
                  <l>Then is in them, and in their mad opinions;</l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:59228:20"/>
                  <l>Which no more credit ſhould find in us, then</l>
                  <l>Poetique fancies, or fanatique dreams.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <l>—For my part;</l>
                  <l>Ere ſince I firſt open'd my eyes to make</l>
                  <l>Inſpection into the darkneſs of</l>
                  <l>Human affairs, and nature, I ſtreight ſaw</l>
                  <l>Nothing was ſuited to our capacities;</l>
                  <l>But ever thought Philoſophers, and ſuch</l>
                  <l>Who give themſelves up to their contemplations.</l>
                  <l>Moſt ignorant, and uſeleſs of all men.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>—They firſt corrupt our natural wit,</l>
                  <l>And judgement with an artificial folly,</l>
                  <l>And then our genuine cuſtoms with learn'd vices.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rome,</hi> as ſhe grew more learned, grew leſs valiant.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Theſe ſtudies in her Senators deſtroy'd</l>
                  <l>That bravery in them, which ſubdu'd the world.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <l>Science, and vice like twins at the ſame time</l>
                  <l>Found birth in her, and grew up to perfection.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>She ow'd her ruin to no other cauſe,</l>
                  <l>Then when ſhe chang'd from <hi>Martial</hi> to be learn'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <l>O let it not be ſaid that this diſeaſe,</l>
                  <l>In the corrupting of the judgement of</l>
                  <l>The great <hi>Valentius,</hi> twice ſhould fatal be</l>
                  <l>Thus to the Roman Name, and Majeſtie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>I am of no ſuch accidents afraid,</l>
                  <l>Where prudence or my will can give me aid.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>We boldly ſhould contemn, not fear thoſe ils,</l>
                  <l>Which cannot be oppoſed by our wills.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>To foſter hopes is a meer vanitie</l>
                  <l>When we foreſee certain our miſerie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <l>A Prince who thus thinks that his State impairs</l>
                  <l>A fruitleſs ſubject gives himſelf of cares.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>He rightly thinks of fortune, who ſuſpects</l>
                  <l>Her various in the perſons ſhe affects.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>The change of fortune rather ſhould erect</l>
                  <l>The ſpirit of an Emperour, then deject.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Unhappy ſtate of Princes! whom her favours</l>
                  <l>Sometimes betray, more then her frowns; for they</l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:59228:21"/>
                  <l>Corrupt us, and our natures mollifie:</l>
                  <l>We gain our honor in adverſitie.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fulvia.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What ſhall I do? ſuſtain the gravitie,</l>
                     <l>And perſon of imperial Majeſtie?</l>
                     <l>Or loſe the hopes elſe of an ardent lover.</l>
                     <l>Rebellious paſſions of my diſtracted ſoul,</l>
                     <l>Fear, love, deſire, envy: why d'ye thus</l>
                     <l>Torment my mind with ſeparated factions?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Though thou art here a moſt unjuſt Uſurper,</l>
                     <l>Love, I'le my ſelf rather ſubmit to thee:</l>
                     <l>Divided power is greater tyranny.</l>
                     <l>Speak then, and hope; happy ſucceſs may make</l>
                     <l>Our impious actions paſs for honorable,</l>
                     <l>Much more the faults of love, which in all breſts</l>
                     <l>Find their Apologies; for no man ſhall,</l>
                     <l>Seeing <hi>Florus,</hi> not abſolve the Criminal:</l>
                     <l>And Ladies, which have known him, cannot chuſe,</l>
                     <l>But ſay the cauſe brings with it the excuſe.</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>To her</hi> Florus.</stage>
                     <l>—O here he comes</l>
                     <l>As I expected! <hi>Florus,</hi> I hope you have</l>
                     <l>Confronted the Original with the</l>
                     <l>Pourtraict I gave you, and are pleaſ'd with both.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Majeſty was not deceiv'd, I ſhall</l>
                  <l>Declare my ſelf an enemie to thoſe,</l>
                  <l>Who ſhall their treacherie practiſe on that beauty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>Now I am happy, I perceive he loves me.</l>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <l>Let no ſuſpicious geloſie torment you;</l>
                  <l>You only then need fear a Rival, when</l>
                  <l>Another <hi>Florus</hi> ſhould be like your ſelf.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>In breſts where love has no admiſſion found,</l>
                  <l>Geloſie can find none; he need not fear</l>
                  <l>A Rival, who no lover is.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>Not you</l>
                  <l>A lover; can I be ſo much deceiv'd?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes; when my reaſon ſhall direct the paſſion.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:59228:21"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>—Love joyn'd with reaſon</l>
                  <l>Is a monſter, and not that noble gheſt,</l>
                  <l>Which ſhould command all in a Princes breſt;</l>
                  <l>Fear, counſel, reaſon either chaſing thence,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe reducing to his obedience.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>My honor then muſt regulate my actions.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>Which never ſhould inſpire a noble heart</l>
                  <l>With cruelty, but rather with compaſſion</l>
                  <l>Of a diſtreſſed Lady. <hi>Florus,</hi> you</l>
                  <l>Knew that to be <hi>Fulvia</hi>'s Picture, I gave you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis true, and as I think by ſome miſtake</l>
                  <l>Unluckily convey'd into theſe hands.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>No Sir, be not deceiv'd, the preſent was</l>
                  <l>Made by mature election.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>I reverence it as your gift, and as</l>
                  <l>The Pourtrait of my Soveraign adore it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>The name of Soveraign is unſuitable</l>
                  <l>To my affection, or my preſent ſtate:</l>
                  <l>Call me your ſervant; that familiar tearm.</l>
                  <l>Becoms him, who predominats o're all</l>
                  <l>The powers of my ſoul.</l>
                  <l>Diſdain not one, who ever hath preſerv'd</l>
                  <l>Her reputation unſtain'd, her faith</l>
                  <l>Inviolated, and to you alone</l>
                  <l>Commits them both; one action of my life</l>
                  <l>Should not reproach me with inconſtancie.</l>
                  <l>Compaſſionate an Empreſs, who entreateth</l>
                  <l>That uſed to command: O <hi>Florus,</hi> put</l>
                  <l>A period to my life, or to my torment.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>—O ye immortal Gods,</l>
                     <stage>aſide.</stage>
                     <l>Can you ſee this offence, and ſuffer it?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I hope your Majeſtie will harbor thoughts</l>
                     <l>Which more become your royal dignitie;</l>
                     <l>And of your own diſhonor, and my ſhame,</l>
                     <l>In hearing mention'd this licentious flame.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>If it be lawleſs, 'twill the more aſpire;</l>
                  <l>Reſiſtance will prove vain to my deſire.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>O Madam, let reaſon triumph above</l>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:59228:22"/>
                  <l>This paſſion, and honor over your love;</l>
                  <l>Think how I am the Subject of <hi>Valentius.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>Sufficient curb to this repulſe ſhould be</l>
                  <l>The thought how a great Empreſs loves you; and</l>
                  <l>Loves you alone; and the Commandreſs of</l>
                  <l>The world ſubmits her ſelf to your commands.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>I can't conceive your Majeſtie as Empreſs,</l>
                  <l>But at that time Wife alſo of my Soveraign.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>If you deſire happineſs, think only</l>
                  <l>Of my Imperial dignitie and power.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>Who by their paſſions thus enſlav'd have loſt</l>
                  <l>Their libertie, cannot of power boaſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>If thou deſpiſeſt an obſequious lover,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt the rage fear of an incenſt Lady.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>I apprehend more danger from the love,</l>
                  <l>Then anger of her who deſpiſes honor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>If thy audacious inſolence contemns</l>
                  <l>My threatnings, their effects ſhall make thee tremble.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>No violence, no hidden treacherie</l>
                  <l>Can affright him, who never fear'd to die.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>—If that which I intend</l>
                  <l>An ignominious death cannot thee move,</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt leſs ſenſe of honor, then of love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>Which cannot be, when the occaſion only,</l>
                  <l>Springs from the hatred of an immodeſt woman.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt feel miſerie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>I can conquer it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt repent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>No, I am ever conſtant.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <p>Ile be reveng'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>I can defend my ſelf.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <p>To ſlight a Lady never was unpuniſht.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>Offence of honor can't be tollerated.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <p>My hatred now ſhall equalize my love.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>And my contempt my former reverence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>O thou unhappy <hi>Fulvia!</hi> what does it</l>
                  <l>Avail thee to be Empreſs of the world,</l>
                  <l>And canſt not make thy ſelf belov'd or fear'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>O miſerable <hi>Florus,</hi> to what purpoſe</l>
                  <l>Can ſerve thy innocence, if thou becom'ſt</l>
                  <l>The odious object of anothers crime.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:59228:22"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ah cruel creature! he is gone: if ever</l>
                     <l>Any had cauſe to murmur againſt nature,</l>
                     <l>'Tis I, in giving him, ſo like <hi>Valentius,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A form and ſhape fatal to my repoſe.</l>
                     <l>I cheriſht the firſt heat, enter'd my breſt</l>
                     <l>Inſenſibly as an acquainted gheſt:</l>
                     <l>But ſeeking after how it did aſpire,</l>
                     <l>I found my nuptial torch lighted this fire:</l>
                     <l>So that I can't reproach my ſelf with ſhame,</l>
                     <l>My firſt and lawful love kindling this flame:</l>
                     <l>Then all the fault's in him, who thus rejects me.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O thou diſdain, the conquerour of love,</l>
                     <l>Which conquers all things elſe, enter my breſt;</l>
                     <l>There, till revenge expel thee, take no reſt:</l>
                     <l>Incenſt by thee, let all my ſpirits aſpire,</l>
                     <l>Mixing in combat with this tyrannique fire</l>
                     <l>For victorie. A Princeſs thus incenſt</l>
                     <l>With love, and rage thus, more is to be fear'd,</l>
                     <l>Then cruel fires, fierce plagues, devouring ſeas,</l>
                     <l>Or what moſt terrifies our human nature.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>To her</hi> Aurelia.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>You Majeſtie is much perplext, that paſſion</l>
                  <l>Is alwaies great, which can't contain it ſelf.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt conceal to her th' unlucky motive</l>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <l>Of my diſturbance. Alas! <hi>Aurelia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>My miſeries are ever fruitful in</l>
                  <l>Producing others: ſcarce my tears are dry'd</l>
                  <l>For the late loſſes of our Family;</l>
                  <l>But I muſt new ſupplies find, to lament</l>
                  <l>The freſh diſgrace now falling on my iſſue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Who can be ſo unjuſt to injure you?</l>
                  <l>Or who can be ſo arrogant t'offend</l>
                  <l>That pow'r, which is ſo armed for revenge?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Valentius;</hi> enemie of his own children,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe I think they're mine, or elſe becauſe</l>
                     <l>They'are Nephews of <hi>Hoſtilius</hi> your Father,</l>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:59228:23"/>
                     <l>Intends that <hi>Florus</hi> ſhall be now advanc't</l>
                     <l>To the Imperial dignitie, to their</l>
                     <l>And my perpetual reproach, that <hi>Florus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Th'oppreſſor of my Father, and who ſeeks</l>
                     <l>The ruin now of yours. <hi>Au.</hi> A happy occaſion</l>
                     <l>Opens a field to the triumphant paſſage</l>
                     <l>Of my revenge; I can my ſelf diſcloſe</l>
                     <l>Now to ſo great an enemie of <hi>Florus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O let that beauteous ſerenitie,</l>
                     <l>Madam, return, which uſ'd t'adorn your looks.</l>
                     <l>—Y'have open'd your diſeaſe</l>
                     <l>To the Phyſitian, who alone can cure you.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>Who you? become of late an enemie</l>
                  <l>To your own father, intereſſed in</l>
                  <l>The quarrel of <hi>Valentius</hi> againſt him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Majeſtie's deceiv'd, I only act</l>
                  <l>A counterfeited part; I have defam'd</l>
                  <l>—My Father as attemptor</l>
                  <l>Upon my virgin modeſtie, that I</l>
                  <l>The better might ſecure his tott'ring power.</l>
                  <l>I fain my ſelf in love with <hi>Florus;</hi> and</l>
                  <l>My flight here to <hi>Valentius,</hi> as my refuge,</l>
                  <l>That I more ſafely may procure their ruin.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aurelia,</hi> we are then in the ſame int'reſt,</l>
                  <l>Will, and affection more conjoin'd, then bloud.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Arſenius</hi> has let me know</l>
                  <l>Of late a ſecret, which will raiſe your wonder;</l>
                  <l>How <hi>Florus</hi> is his Son, and how he is</l>
                  <l>In love with me, ſeeking a mutual love;</l>
                  <l>Which underſtanding, with notice of my Father</l>
                  <l>I fill'd the old mans head with hopes, and joy</l>
                  <l>Of my affection for his Son, to whom he has</l>
                  <stage>ſhews her a letter.</stage>
                  <l>A letter writ here on that very ſubject,</l>
                  <l>Apt either to make him deſert his Prince,</l>
                  <l>In hope of gaining me; or elſe t'accuſe him</l>
                  <l>Of treaſon in his correſpondence with</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Arſenius</hi> enemie of <hi>Valentius;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who thus abuſ'd ſhall ſee himſelf depriv'd</l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:59228:23"/>
                  <l>Of this his Gen'ral, our great Adverſary.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>My Brothers preſent danger, and my Sons</l>
                  <l>Diſgrace, whoſe fame <hi>Florus</hi> eclipſes, makes</l>
                  <l>Him ſubject of my hatred; and the mem'ry</l>
                  <l>Of my poor Father, murderd by <hi>Valentius,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Makes him alike. <hi>Au.</hi> Madam, then let us ſtrive</l>
                  <l>To be reveng'd of both;</l>
                  <l>And with an emulation, who ſhall put</l>
                  <l>Her malice into ſpeedieſt execution;</l>
                  <l>Not doubting of ſucceſs: 'Tis great aſſurance</l>
                  <l>To thoſe, who ſeek revenge, to have ſo faithful</l>
                  <l>Companions in the ſtratagems, as you have.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis true my dear <hi>Aurelia,</hi> let me embrace thee</l>
                  <l>For this thy brav'ry; though I envy it,</l>
                  <l>So far advancing thy unriper years.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>This day ſhall ſhew here what the furious rage</l>
                  <l>Of an ambitious Lady can produce;</l>
                  <l>And the intereſt and geloſie of State,</l>
                  <l>And emulation, Madam, of your glory.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>Expect from me all, that can be expected</l>
                  <l>From a contriving ſubtle wit, and cunning</l>
                  <l>Hypocriſie joyn'd with a perfect malice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Let <hi>Florus,</hi> let <hi>Valentius</hi> perceive</l>
                  <l>Th' entrance of <hi>Aurelia</hi> in their Camp.</l>
                  <l>Let fear and modeſty, companions of</l>
                  <l>Our ſex, ſo much enclin'd to virtue, be</l>
                  <l>Now caſt off by the thoughts of our revenge.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>My paſſion ſhall eſteem no ſin unliſenc'd.</l>
                  <l>In me let one crime ſtill beget another;</l>
                  <l>And let it not be thought a crime, which does</l>
                  <l>Not multiply it ſelf in many others;</l>
                  <l>And ever with increaſe, the latter greateſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam miſtake not; and let nothing paſs</l>
                  <l>With us for criminal, but what is virtuous.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis the delightful fruit of vice to think,</l>
                  <l>That no vice, which is cauſ'd by intereſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>True of our ſelves, better then that of ſtate;</l>
                  <l>Which no great Prince values at any rate,</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:59228:24"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>They never elſe in Court or Camp would find,</l>
                  <l>With all their pomp, tranquility of mind.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis on this ground that I'le prepare to act</l>
                  <l>Thoſe things I cannot think, unleſs enrag'd.</l>
                  <l>Poſteritie ſhall ever curſe, though ſcarce</l>
                  <l>Believe that, which I'le put in execution.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>Compar'd with me thou ſhalt as innocent</l>
                  <l>Appear, and did the ſtate but know how high</l>
                  <l>The provocation is of my diſdain,</l>
                  <l>It would with trembling fear the conſequence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Who injur'd me the favor ſhall not have</l>
                  <l>To die, unleſs that I accompanie</l>
                  <l>That death with an eternal infamie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>That merits not the title of revenge,</l>
                  <l>When we deſtroy and enemie, and give</l>
                  <l>Leave to his reputation ſtill to live.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Valentius. Florus. Statilius. Honorus, with Court-Attendants.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Since not as yet poſſeſt of <hi>Rome,</hi> we cannot</l>
                  <l>Expreſs our joy with uſual feſtivals,</l>
                  <l>For this adoption of <hi>Florus</hi> in the Empire;</l>
                  <l>Lets ſee what ſports, and what divertiſements</l>
                  <l>Our Camp affords us in our ſlaves and captives.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Here very conveniently may be brought in ſome divertiſements of the Stage.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>I never lik't the fancie of <hi>Auguſtus;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor of ſome other Princes, who have from</l>
                  <l>The vices, imperfections of ſucceſſors</l>
                  <l>(Sometimes their Sons, Brothers, neareſt Allies)</l>
                  <l>Sought to illuſtrate to poſteritie</l>
                  <l>Their ſhameful glory, ſo injurious to them,</l>
                  <l>And to the preſent age: A ſolid virtue</l>
                  <l>Needs no ſuch foyl, or ſhadow to ſet off</l>
                  <l>Her beauteous luſtre; and this is the reaſon,</l>
                  <l>Why I omitting my own iſſue joyn'd</l>
                  <l>To me in bloud, not virtue, <hi>Florus,</hi> have</l>
                  <l>Deſtin'd thee for my ſucceſſor; and to morrow</l>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:59228:24"/>
                  <l>Companion, and Collegue in my great Empire.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Majeſty declares in this Election,</l>
                  <l>No paſſion has an influence o're your judgement.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Since 'tis not in my power to create him</l>
                     <l>Heir of my bloud, I'le make him of my glorie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But <hi>Florus</hi> why amaz'd? thy merit ſhould</l>
                     <l>Prevent thy marvel at thy high advancement:</l>
                     <l>Honor ſhould ne'r ſurprize a noble breſt,</l>
                     <l>But enter as a long expected gheſt.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>My ſilence was th' effect of grief, and wonder;</l>
                  <l>The laſt occaſion'd thus to ſee a Father</l>
                  <l>Deveſt himſelf of natural affections,</l>
                  <l>To repreſent a Prince more abſolute:</l>
                  <l>My ſorrow from the ſenſe of envy ſprings,</l>
                  <l>Which will purſue ſo great proſperitie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Your grief were juſter, if your exploits had not</l>
                  <l>Deſerved envy; and your wonder, if</l>
                  <l>Your merit had not forced this Election.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>he need not envie fear, who by his actions</l>
                  <l>Worthy of envie has ſecur'd himſelf</l>
                  <l>In a ſafe ſtation, above the reach of envie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>The title of <hi>Caeſarean</hi> Majeſtie</l>
                  <l>Is too illuſtrious for my extraction,</l>
                  <l>The charge too weighty for theſe ſhoulders; which</l>
                  <l>I fear will faint under their glorious burden.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <l>Who firſt knows how to rule himſelf, like you,</l>
                  <l>Seems deſtin'd by the providence of heavens</l>
                  <l>For the command of Scepters, and of Empires.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Fear nothing <hi>Florus;</hi> chearfully aſſume</l>
                  <l>This greatneſs, as thy valors recompence;</l>
                  <l>A purchaſe, which with loſs of bloud, life, honor</l>
                  <l>So often is ſought after by ambition:</l>
                  <l>For the proud man finds that the boiſtrous floud,</l>
                  <l>Which rowls him to this Port, ſtill runs in bloud.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:59228:25"/>
               <head>ACT. IV.</head>
               <stage>Valentius. Carbo. Antonia.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>NOw I perceive, as thou haſt told me, that</l>
                  <l>This my erroneous purſuing of</l>
                  <l>The cuſtoms of Princes my Anceſtors,</l>
                  <l>(Which makes me as I write and ſpeak with pens,</l>
                  <l>And Tongues of other men; juſt ſo I hear</l>
                  <l>My informations with the ears of others)</l>
                  <l>Has led me in a labyrinth of errors,</l>
                  <l>Where truth could never find me out, had you</l>
                  <l>Not been her truſty guides. For thou O <hi>Carbo</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Muſt be content to have this noble Lady</l>
                  <l>Companion in thy glory.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>I am proud of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>'Twas ſhe who firſt made known to me, from whence</l>
                  <l>Aroſe the clouds, which have of late eclipſt</l>
                  <l>The mirth, and beautie of my deareſt Conſort:</l>
                  <l>I ſay 'twas ſhe; prepare thy faith to hear</l>
                  <l>Far greater wonders, than thou haſt related.</l>
                  <l>This Traytor <hi>Florus</hi> in the preſence of</l>
                  <l>This noble Lady has ſolicited</l>
                  <l>My Empreſs, O horror! to betray</l>
                  <l>My honor; nay ſtartle not; that's my part,</l>
                  <l>Whom the world falſely calls the great <hi>Valentius.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I was ſurpriz'd; but thinking how the greateſt</l>
                  <l>Of vices is ingratitude; there's none</l>
                  <l>Of which I think he cannot be found guilty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>This I confeſs: but alaſs! here his utmoſt</l>
                  <l>Cruelty ſhould have ſpar'd his Prince: I am</l>
                  <l>The ſoul diffuſ'd through the vaſt body of</l>
                  <l>The Empire, thus expoſ'd in all parts to</l>
                  <l>His wounds, and injuries; at leaſt herein</l>
                  <l>He ſhould have had compaſſion of his friend</l>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:59228:25"/>
                  <l>His Benefactor, Father by adoption;</l>
                  <l>Which merits more then if I were by nature.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, he has told me, he eſteem'd all things</l>
                  <l>Lawful to gain an Empire, or a Miſtreſs:</l>
                  <l>And in a ſcorning manner oft would ſay;</l>
                  <l>In other things let juſtice be obſerv'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>O ye immortal Gods! why has your care</l>
                  <l>Given us a touchſtone to diſtinguiſh our</l>
                  <l>Adulterate gold, and no mark to diſcern</l>
                  <l>The treacherous hearts of falſe perfidious men.</l>
                  <l>— If this be true;</l>
                  <l>Confound him with your ſharpeſt thunderbolt:</l>
                  <l>But 'tis too true; and if I further ſtay</l>
                  <l>To queſtion it; I fear I ſhall become</l>
                  <l>Procurour of thoſe dire events upon me,</l>
                  <l>Portended in my laſt nights dreams to happen</l>
                  <l>Within ſo ſhort a time.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Antonia</hi> retire: I'le have a care</l>
                  <l>To vindicate my honor: his proud Laurels,</l>
                  <l>Which from <hi>Joves</hi> thunder are ſecure, I'le blaſt.</l>
                  <l>But let this ſecret make no further progreſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant,</speaker>
                  <l>My prudent care ſhall not fail to correct</l>
                  <l>This fault, to which our ſex is incident.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>A Prince, who tolerates a known diſgrace,</l>
                  <l>Becomes the ſubject of the vulgar ſcorn.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>Honor, once ſought to be betray'd, is never</l>
                  <l>Secure, ſo long as the Offendor lives.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Geloſie entred in a Prince, no other</l>
                  <l>Aſſiſtant needs, to haſten his revenge.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>Which, when it is of a ſlow pace, we find</l>
                  <l>'Tis ſigne of weakneſs in a Princes mind.</l>
                  <l>Let him th' effects Sir of your anger prove,</l>
                  <l>Who thus hath undervalued your love;</l>
                  <l>In prudent Monarques, like your ſelf, t'appear</l>
                  <l>Not to be fear'd, ſhould be your only fear.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>You Majeſty's perplext.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>But why ſhould I</l>
                  <l>So low thoughts of my ſelf have; and ſo high</l>
                  <l>Of his bold inſolent temeritie.</l>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:59228:26"/>
                  <l>Good <hi>Carbo</hi> have the patience to repeat</l>
                  <l>Thy ſtory over; though in it ev'ry paſſage</l>
                  <l>Creates new wounds, and ulcers in my ſoul.</l>
                  <l>Thou ſaidſt, the Maſter of my light Cavalrie,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Macrinus,</hi> was not Father of this <hi>Florus;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But that <hi>Arſenius,</hi> the ſworn enemy of</l>
                  <l>My perſon, and my dignitie has made</l>
                  <l>The world the preſent of this diſſembling Monſter:</l>
                  <l>Can this be ſo?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Majeſtie may reſt</l>
                  <l>Can this be ſo? <hi>Car.</hi> Your Majeſtie may reſt</l>
                  <l>Aſſur'd I heard it from his own relation;</l>
                  <l>And how beſides he has in a diſguiſe</l>
                  <l>Converſt here with him in our Camp; where he</l>
                  <l>Aſſur'd him of the conſent of <hi>Hoſtilius</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For his obtaining of the fair <hi>Aurelia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Idol of his ſoul;</l>
                  <l>With the rich dowrie of the Roman Empire.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Which his pernicious hopes ſecurely ſtreight</l>
                  <l>Devour'd, with conſentment to my ruine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes; and with invitation to my ſelf,</l>
                  <l>Joyning with him, to take part with <hi>Hoſtilius.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>See where the Empreſs comes: I take my leave.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit,</stage>
               <stage>Valentius. Fulvia. Antonia.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>Now if, <hi>Antonia,</hi> as thy promiſe was,</l>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <l>Thou haſt diſtill'd the poiſon in his ears;</l>
                  <l>I ſhall perceive ſtreight by the operation.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>My deareſt <hi>Fulvia,</hi> ſince all griefs and ſorrows</l>
                  <l>Divided are betwixt the Wife and Huſband,</l>
                  <l>Th' occaſions alſo ſhould be ſo; if then</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Antonia</hi>'s care without your intimation</l>
                  <l>Has let me know the cauſe of your diſtemper,</l>
                  <l>I muſt obtain her pardon; let then thy</l>
                  <l>Former ſerenity of looks diſpel</l>
                  <l>Thoſe clouds of ſorrow from that brow to mine;</l>
                  <l>Where they hang thick already; but I'le have</l>
                  <l>Them waſht away in bloud of the offendors.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>With whoſe let mine be joyn'd; Sir 'tis the only</l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:59228:26"/>
                  <l>Favor I beg here on my knees; by all</l>
                  <stage>kneels.</stage>
                  <l>The former merits, with which the conſtant duty</l>
                  <l>Of an obedient Wife has e're been able</l>
                  <l>T'oblige a Huſband; by the riſing hopes</l>
                  <l>Of young <hi>Valentius;</hi> and the other pledges</l>
                  <l>And fruits of our ſo conſtant loves, till now</l>
                  <l>By this accurſed accident diſturb'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>They are not: riſe then; O let me not ſee</l>
                  <stage>takes her up.</stage>
                  <l>My idol thus bow, and encline to me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sure you look on me with falſe eyes, or elſe</l>
                     <l>You ſee me chang'd into a loathſome creature:</l>
                     <l>Suſpicion of guilt in an Empreſs makes her</l>
                     <l>Seem foul, and guiltie to her felf and others.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>So I am in effect: a Viper though</l>
                     <l>He caſts no poiſon forth; his very touches</l>
                     <l>Are venemous: th'offring to embrace me</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Florus</hi> has methinks with leproſie</l>
                     <l>Infected all my parts. Good Sir have mercie</l>
                     <stage>kneels again.</stage>
                     <l>On your poor <hi>Fulvia</hi> here; and let me die;</l>
                     <l>When life is now my greateſt miſerie.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>His bloud ſhall rather ſatisfie th' offence,</l>
                  <l>Who treſpaſt on thy ſpotleſs innocence:</l>
                  <l>And though he ſeemeth at too cheap a rate</l>
                  <l>By ſingle death his crime to expiate;</l>
                  <l>'Tis recompenc't at once to ſee him die,</l>
                  <l>And live in a perpetual infamie;</l>
                  <l>Whilſt thou the beſt of women; glorie of</l>
                  <stage>embraces her.</stage>
                  <l>The preſent age, and honor of thy ſex,</l>
                  <l>Shalt like a ſtar of the firſt magnitude,</l>
                  <l>Shine glorious in the firmament of honor.</l>
                  <l>However yet, my deareſt <hi>Fulvia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The heavens in their happineſs delay:</l>
                  <l>Thy preſence, though ſo much deſired there,</l>
                  <l>T'inſtruct the age is neceſſary here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>My noble Lord, my dutie,</l>
                  <l>So hitherto obſequious to your will,</l>
                  <l>Shall ſtrive then to obey your laſt commands.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>O now thou ſpeakſt like <hi>Fulvia,</hi> and thy ſelf:</l>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:59228:27"/>
                  <l>Thy paſſions can never long transforme thee:</l>
                  <l>Come let us go to my Pavilion, and</l>
                  <l>Conſult upon the manner, how to put</l>
                  <l>In ſpeedy execution our revenge:</l>
                  <l>The juſt effects of which ſhall never ceaſe,</l>
                  <l>Till in the Traitors bloud I find my peace</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Florus. Honorius.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis ſtrange methinks, <hi>Honorius,</hi> that you,</l>
                  <l>An <hi>Epicurean</hi> by Sect ſhould be</l>
                  <l>An enemy of love; the greateſt pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>When once obtain'd, in the enjoyment of</l>
                  <l>What we call perfect beauty; a happineſs</l>
                  <l>So frequently deſir'd, ſo ſeldom found.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>The nature of true pleaſure can't conſiſt</l>
                  <l>In the delights of love, which leave the ſoul</l>
                  <l>Not ſatisfi'd, when the moſt ſatiated;</l>
                  <l>Whilſt in her interchangeably there fight</l>
                  <l>Reſtleſs diſguſt, and reſtleſs appetite.</l>
                  <l>True pleaſures no remorſe, but leave behind</l>
                  <l>Them ſtill a grateful odor in the mind.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>They ill diſcourſe of love, who are no lovers.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>It troubles me to ſee the royal fort</l>
                  <l>Of noble <hi>Florus</hi> heart thus yielded up.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis given up to him, who conquers all things;</l>
                  <l>And will in time the brave <hi>Honorius</hi> breſt,</l>
                  <l>Where virtue keeps ſo ſtrong a garriſon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>It muſt be weak, if ſo contemptible</l>
                  <l>An Adverſary can his entrance force.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>Neglect of the Enemy deſtroys the valiant:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>The fear of him dejecteth noble ſpirits.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>Who apprehends his Adverſary may</l>
                  <l>Preſerve his honor, though he loſe the day.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>Eſteem of him is diſtruſt in our ſelves.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>A prudent fear companion is of valor.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis rather of an irreſolved mind.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:59228:27"/>
               <stage>
                  <hi>To them</hi> Aurelia.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>But ſtay, behold: here breaks the beauteous light,</l>
                  <l>Which will theſe difficulties cleer.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Honorius</hi> ſtand firm; what means this change?</l>
                  <stage>Honorius <hi>ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd at her beauty.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>Let not thy actions contradict thy words.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>My hearts unmov'd: but the external ſenſe</l>
                  <l>In ſuch ſurpriſals has no ſure defence.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yonder he comes; his eyes are fixt on mine;</l>
                     <l>Thoſe falſe lights, which will lead him to his ruine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Love and Diſdain, two raging firebrands,</l>
                     <l>Are of the mind; their common reſidence</l>
                     <l>Is in the heart; but raiſe a general</l>
                     <l>Diſturbance in the ſoul, confounding all</l>
                     <l>Her faculties. They are of equal force,</l>
                     <l>Contending for the prize with emulation;</l>
                     <l>But in effect and nature contrary;</l>
                     <l>The one producing hatred, and the other</l>
                     <l>Gentle affection: when theſe fierce Combatants</l>
                     <l>In duel are; the heart too narrow a field</l>
                     <l>For two ſuch Foes groans languiſhing in torment,</l>
                     <l>Till one the victor ſhall ſubdue the other;</l>
                     <l>As here Diſdain has Love in me, by force</l>
                     <l>Compelling me to act a damned part</l>
                     <l>Againſt my nature, conſcience, and my heart.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>My honor does depend upon his death;</l>
                     <stage>aſide.</stage>
                     <l>And yet perchance my life depends on his.</l>
                     <l>But I am now engag'd paſt all retreat.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>O my <hi>Aurelia</hi> (pardon this preſumption)</l>
                  <l>If I am bold to call you ſo upon</l>
                  <l>So new acquaintance; my love's of longer date.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>And ſo is mine; however that love's poor,</l>
                  <l>Which time requires to grow up to perfection.</l>
                  <l>Mine of another nature was; at once</l>
                  <l>Finding conception, and maturity;</l>
                  <l>Both at firſt ſight of you. <hi>Flo.</hi> But what was ſtranger;</l>
                  <l>I found my heart enflamed from the ſhadow,</l>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:59228:28"/>
                  <l>And picture of you only: from dead colours</l>
                  <l>Love firſt found life in me: I ſelt the heat,</l>
                  <l>Before I ſaw the light: wonder not then</l>
                  <l>If I ſtand trembling in the preſence of</l>
                  <l>My Goddeſs, when the luſtre of her only</l>
                  <l>Image I could not with theſe eyes ſuſtain;</l>
                  <l>Which from that time is ever in my thoughts.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis long, amongſt your very enemies,</l>
                  <l>That fame has painted your illuſtrious perſon,</l>
                  <l>Heroique actions (though perchance with colours</l>
                  <l>Defective from the life) and your great merit:</l>
                  <l>Wonder not then, that I forgetting my</l>
                  <l>Imperial dignity, and virgin bluſhes;</l>
                  <l>And other ceremonious reſtraints,</l>
                  <l>So ſuddenly am thus become your captive.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>Can this be true, <hi>Aurelia?</hi> can the heavens</l>
                  <l>So prodigally pour on me their bleſſings.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>To ſee you; and to fall in love with you,</l>
                  <l>Sir, things are different; but by thoſe heavens</l>
                  <l>You mentioned, happened to me in one moment.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>Why ſhould we fear, that time ſhould then deſtroy,</l>
                  <l>What time did not produce; that's our affection.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis true; but violent flames, like ours, we ſee</l>
                  <l>Conſume their nouriſhing fuels, and themſelves;</l>
                  <l>And we think happier thoſe, whom love inſpires</l>
                  <l>With moderate heats, with moderate deſires:</l>
                  <l>Which keep themſelves alive like glowing fires.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>My life, my ſoul, my dear <hi>Aurelia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Make here no mention of ſiniſter ſurmiſes.</l>
                  <l>My breſt not comprehending well the greatneſs</l>
                  <l>Of my felicitie, gives place too faſt</l>
                  <l>Already to my fears. I cannot think</l>
                  <l>My fortune unforeſeen will conſtant prove.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir you may fix her, if youl execute</l>
                  <l>What the ſenſe of this Letter will perſwade you.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Gives him a Letter, which. he reads as follows.</stage>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:59228:28"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>Florus, <hi>I have, through my affection, to you, reſtored to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty your friend, and my priſoner of war</hi> Honorius; <hi>who has diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd to me your ſecret love of our Princeſs</hi> Aurelia; <hi>from whom I have obtain'd a correſpondent affection for you, by the conſent of her Father: who much deſires to adopt ſuch a Son for his Succeſſor in the Empire. The affection, and intereſt you have in the Army, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters a fair occaſion of revenging your ſelf of a cruel adverſary of your Father, by diſarming</hi> Valentius <hi>of his chiefeſt forces. I expect your ſodain anſwer, and concurrence to your own happineſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <stage>Arſenius.</stage>
                  <l>What's this I ſee? new treacheries againſt me?</l>
                  <l>This Letter is writ by <hi>Arſenius.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>How comes <hi>Aurelia</hi> to preſent it, who</l>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <l>Declares her ſelf enemy of <hi>Hoſtilius.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Can ſhe diſſemble? a perſon of ſuch honor?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>—What ſtrange ſuſpenſion is this which I ſee,</l>
                  <l>Sir, in your thoughts, and looks ſuddenly chang'd?</l>
                  <l>Be reſolute; the queſtion's only here,</l>
                  <l>Whether you will concur in the procuring</l>
                  <l>Your Father's happineſs, your own, and mine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>I can no amorous correſpondence purchaſe</l>
                  <l>At ſuch a rate, thus forfeiting my honor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir 'twas plebeian folly</l>
                  <l>Which firſt raiſ'd Idols; and then worſhipt them;</l>
                  <l>And amongſt others this of honor; but</l>
                  <l>I hope your thoughts fly higher, not confind</l>
                  <l>Within the limits of law, cuſtom, juſtice;</l>
                  <l>Shackles for Common people, not for Princes;</l>
                  <l>Great Ravagers of ſea, and land like you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>Unhappy <hi>Florus!</hi> what a coeleſtial ſhape</l>
                  <l>A Fury here has taken to betray thee.</l>
                  <l>—Vile woman take thy Letter;</l>
                  <stage>throws back the Letter.</stage>
                  <l>Inveigle ſome leſs cautious with theſe arts.</l>
                  <l>I lov'd thee, whil'ſt I thought thee lover of</l>
                  <l>Thy honor; but do now as much deteſt thee,</l>
                  <l>As I do thy moſt deteſtable crime.</l>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:59228:29"/>
                  <l>I could now kill thee; for though little honor</l>
                  <stage>half draws.</stage>
                  <l>VVould in't appear; the action commendable</l>
                  <l>Would be to purge the world of ſo infectious</l>
                  <l>A Peſtilence: yet live; thou wilt reſent</l>
                  <stage>puts up.</stage>
                  <l>Thus, I believe, the greater puniſhment.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aurelia;</hi> now 'tis time to come to action;</l>
                     <l>Repentance is too late: crimes of this nature,</l>
                     <l>If once begun, are ne'r ſecure till finiſht.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Friends, Officers, Commanders, haſten</l>
                     <l>To the defence of a diſtreſſed Lady,</l>
                     <stage>cries out near the Tents.</stage>
                     <l>An innocent Virgin, an unhappy Princeſs.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>To them</hi> Valentius, Statilius, Fulvia, &amp;c. <hi>as out of the Praetorian Tents.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>VVaſt you <hi>Aurelia,</hi> who made this outcry?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yes, great <hi>Valentius,</hi> twas I; 'twas I;</l>
                     <l>The moſt unfortunate <hi>Aurelia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To whom no place I ſee will afford refuge:</l>
                     <l>For what ſecurity can I my ſelf</l>
                     <l>Promiſe from your protection, when your Gen'ral,</l>
                     <l>My Fathers private friend, threatens by force</l>
                     <l>To bring me back to his Camp, perſwaded by</l>
                     <l>This Letter, which he has caſt into my hands,</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>gives the Letter to</hi> Valentius.</stage>
                     <l>That I fondly in love muſt yield my felf</l>
                     <l>His prey, to ſatisfie my Fathers pleaſure,</l>
                     <l>My preſent enemie; who perſecutes,</l>
                     <l>My honor, dearer to me then my life.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>His rage has been ſo violent on my</l>
                     <l>Refuſal, that he drew his ſword upon me;</l>
                     <l>A poor diſtreſſed woman!</l>
                     <l>Deny this Villain if thou canſt; ſee there</l>
                     <l>His ſword yet ſcarcely ſheath'd.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir hear me ſpeak.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Perfidious Traitor, interrupt her not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>—Sir I hope</l>
                     <l>You'l as a Prince your patronage afford</l>
                     <stage>kneels.</stage>
                     <l>To the diſtreſt, and as a Judge condemn</l>
                     <l>So foul a criminal.</l>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:59228:29"/>
                     <l>Look on me not as Daughter of a Tyrant,</l>
                     <l>And of your Enemie; but as the Niece</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Fulvia,</hi> your pious virtuous Empreſs.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>riſes.</stage>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If I cannot obtain revenge, I'le rather</l>
                     <l>Chuſe gloriouſly to die by my own hands,</l>
                     <l>Then afford matter to anothers crime;</l>
                     <l>Here, I ſwear by thoſe Gods, who ſee me injur'd.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>Your Majeſty will let me ſpeak.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>I will not.</l>
                  <l>O ye coeleſtinl powers, in what ſtrange darkneſs</l>
                  <l>Are our human affairs involv'd: from you</l>
                  <l>We know not what to ask, or what to fear.</l>
                  <l>So off our wiſhes prove our fatal ruin:</l>
                  <l>So oft by what we feard, we are preſerv'd.</l>
                  <l>I never ſought your favours with ſuch fervent</l>
                  <l>Prayers for my ſelf, as for this monſter; whom</l>
                  <l>Mov'd with a falſe inſpired love, I have</l>
                  <l>From his green years here foſter'd in my boſom;</l>
                  <l>Preſerv'd his beauteous youth from all abuſe,</l>
                  <l>And afterward, before his age admitted,</l>
                  <l>Heap't honors on him to afford him matter,</l>
                  <l>In all the three parts of the world, of Triumph;</l>
                  <l>Where I have made his name glorious and fear'd,</l>
                  <l>That at the laſt I might fear him my ſelf.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>—Sir I could wiſh you'd read.</l>
                  <l>His Fathers private Letter; but alas!</l>
                  <l>I fear 'twill turn your paſſion into rage.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>I will; to diſarm him of all excuſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>He is reading the letter at ſome diſtance.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>Now I triumph to ſee thy boaſting fate</l>
                  <l>Bow, and ſubmit it ſelf to <hi>Fulvia</hi>'s hate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au,</speaker>
                  <l>And from this moment <hi>I</hi> eſteem my ſelf <hi>To</hi> Florus <hi>apart.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Happy; now I have made thee miſerable.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>O cruel creatures, leave me to my ſelf.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>No; I'le torment thee here; when thou art dead,</l>
                  <l>My Brothers ghoſt ſhall act that part; whom thou</l>
                  <l>Inhumanly didſt murder in cold bloud.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>'Twas only by the chance of war he fell.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Know once, thou wert the only object of</l>
                  <l>My love, as now of hatred; which when any</l>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:59228:30"/>
                  <l>Remorſe of conſcience would extinguiſh in me,</l>
                  <stage>Plucks forth the bloudy handkerchef.</stage>
                  <l>See here; thus with that bloud I wip't away.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <p>O my revenge, ſweeter then life, or love.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <p>O how my joy increaſes with his torment.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>How much I was deceiv'd; he ſhall ſtreight die.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>In read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the letter</hi> Val. <hi>often ſtamps and cries Traitor. Shews the letter.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>My deareſt <hi>Fulvia,</hi> what's the matter with him?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <p>He rages only to ſee himſelf diſcover'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, will your Majeſty be pleaſ'd to hear me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Speak arrogant Traitor then; only in anſwer</l>
                  <l>To what I ask: is this the writing of</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Arſenius?</hi> confeſs; is he thy Father?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>Should I deny <hi>Arſenius,</hi> Sir, to be</l>
                  <l>My Father, I ſhould be ingrateful to him</l>
                  <l>Who gave me being; which the Gods defend.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>It was thy choice then rather to expreſs</l>
                  <l>Thy gratitude to him, a publick Rebel,</l>
                  <l>And Traitor to his Country, then to me,</l>
                  <l>The common Father of her; thy peculiar,</l>
                  <l>And ſo great benefactor. See, <hi>Statilius,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To have <hi>Honorius</hi> found out; as I</l>
                  <l>Believe confederate in this treaſon; and</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Macrinus,</hi> who, perſwading us he was</l>
                  <l>The Father of him, has conceal'd his true</l>
                  <l>Extraction.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhall obey.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy crimes ſo horrid are, that with the greateſt</l>
                  <l>I can't reproche thee; neither ſtands it with</l>
                  <l>The reputation of a man of honor,</l>
                  <l>Much leſs a Princes dignity to ſpeak them.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>To them</hi> Honorius. Arſenius.</stage>
                  <l>—Oh here opportunely comes another</l>
                  <l>Conſpirator: Tell me, vile man, the reaſon</l>
                  <stage>To Honorius,</stage>
                  <l>Of purchaſing thy dear-bought libertie</l>
                  <l>With proſtitution of thy honor; 'twas</l>
                  <l>Thou, who diſcoverdſt to <hi>Arſenius,</hi> how</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Florus</hi> was ready to betray me, when</l>
                  <l>He ſhould obtain <hi>Aurelia</hi> for his bed.</l>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:59228:30"/>
                  <l>Therfore thou ſhalt fall with him: it were pity</l>
                  <l>That cruel death ſhould ſeparate that pair,</l>
                  <l>Which treacherous friendſhip has ſo faſt united.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <l>Unlucky ſon! thus betray'd by thy ſelf;</l>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <l>And I become a miſerable Father,</l>
                  <l>In only ſeeking a Sons happineſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>What he's aſtoniſht to be thus found out.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>No: 'tis to have my faith ſuſpected only,</l>
                  <l>Who with expence of bloud ſo oft have purchaſt</l>
                  <l>The reputation of my Prince.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <l>Infortunate <hi>Arſenius!</hi> conſtrain'd</l>
                  <l>Here to accuſe thy ſelf of guilt and die</l>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <l>Diſhonor'd, to expreſs a loving Father</l>
                  <l>To him; who ſcarce vouchſaf'd to be thy Son.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>When once thy actions have deceiv'd me, I</l>
                  <l>Should too incautious be, to be ſurpriz'd</l>
                  <l>With the fair language of diſcover'd traitors.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ah, cruel Prince! if there be treacherie, tis mine;</l>
                     <l>'Tis mine alone; <hi>Florus</hi> is guilty of</l>
                     <l>No other crime, but diſobeying of</l>
                     <l>A Father in obedience to thee;</l>
                     <l>Which has alike <hi>Honorius</hi> made ingrateful</l>
                     <l>To me, the author of his libertie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I am <hi>Arſenius:</hi> and though I was</l>
                     <stage>Plucks off his diſguiſe.</stage>
                     <l>Injuriouſly upon a falſe ſuſpicion</l>
                     <l>Baniſh'd the Empire; I'le confeſs my ſelf</l>
                     <l>A criminal, to ſave the innocent.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O ſpare a Son; become an enemy</l>
                     <l>To his own Father, to obey his Prince.</l>
                     <l>O ſpare a Friend; whoſe gallant braverie</l>
                     <l>So nobly ſcorn'd my treacherous curteſie.</l>
                     <l>Let me fall; with my bloud theſe gray hairs ſtain,</l>
                     <l>Who thus alone have my own ruine wrought;</l>
                     <l>The fitteſt ſacrifice for thy revenge.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Arſenius! Arſenius</hi> here! why this clears all my doubts.</p>
                  <stage>Says this in amaze.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Unhappy Father; this is to reproach</l>
                     <l>A weakneſs in me, not to think this heart</l>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:59228:31"/>
                     <l>Sufficiently couragious to ſuſtain</l>
                     <l>The injuſt indignation of one man.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Let not your Majeſty deceive your ſelf;</l>
                     <l>Had I not been incautious in my love,</l>
                     <l>My Father had not incur'd this ſuſpiſition</l>
                     <l>Of treacherie; not cauſ'd by malice, but</l>
                     <l>Compaſſion of raſh folly in a Son.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Florus,</hi> this language is offenſive to</l>
                  <l>Thy virtue, and our friendſhip, in ſuppoſing</l>
                  <l>Your ſelf the leaſt way guilty; in your life</l>
                  <l>If you to envy ſubject were, in death</l>
                  <l>Be not to infamy. Let glory triumph</l>
                  <l>Over thy nature; let thy Father periſh,</l>
                  <l>Thy Friend, thy ſelf; but let thy honor live.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <l>My only Son, let me fall by thy hands:</l>
                  <l>Compaſſion 'tis, not cruelty to take</l>
                  <l>My life in my old age, and ſave my honor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>Take rather, Sir, that life, which you have giv'n</l>
                  <l>To me now for my miſerie; already</l>
                  <l>I for my glory have liv'd long enough.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ho.</speaker>
                  <l>Cheer up friends; 'tis for us, who gloriouſly</l>
                  <l>Have known the way to live ſo many years,</l>
                  <l>Eaſie to die like Romans in a moment.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <p>Why thus amuſ'd?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <p>What do you ruminate?</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>To</hi> Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentius.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, as the caſe ſtands now, your only counſel</l>
                  <l>Is to take none.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <p>But think of execution.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>As a ſhip ſeeming with her ful-blown ſails</l>
                     <l>To make a high and rapid courſe, ſometimes</l>
                     <l>Is checkt, and drawn back by an unknown current:</l>
                     <l>So I methinks now ardently purſuing</l>
                     <l>Revenge; thus inſtigated by my reaſon,</l>
                     <l>And paſſion feel within me ſecret motives,</l>
                     <l>Which would retard my will. But I muſt break</l>
                     <l>Through theſe impediments. They all ſhall die</l>
                     <l>And from thee, <hi>Fulvia,</hi> ſhall receive their ſentence.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou for thy anſwering my great benefits</l>
                     <l>With an unparallel'd ingratitude.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>To</hi> Flous.</stage>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou, who preferd'ſt before thy loyaltie</l>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:59228:31"/>
                     <l>A friendſhip ſo diſhonorable, ſhalt,</l>
                     <l>Now ſee the fruits of thy unlucky choice.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>To.</hi> Honorius.</stage>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And thou inur'd to treaſon, who at laſt</l>
                     <l>Betrayd'ſt thy ſelf, ſhalt ſee how the juſt heavens</l>
                     <l>Convert thy crimes into thy puniſhment.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>To</hi> Arſenius.</stage>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thus Treaſon is diſcover'd in the birth:</l>
                     <l>The Gods of heaven protect the Gods of earth.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Ex.</hi> Val. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </stage>
               <stage>Florus. Honorius. Arſenius.</stage>
               <stage>manent.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <l>Come let our minds be cheerful: now they ſhall</l>
                  <l>No longer priſ'ners be; we are juſt ſailing</l>
                  <l>Out of the narrow channel of this life</l>
                  <l>Into the Port, or rather boundleſs Ocean</l>
                  <l>Of everlaſting, unreſtrained freedom.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis true; we are now on the confines of</l>
                  <l>That vaſt, immenſe, inconfin'd libertie,</l>
                  <l>Which men call Death.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Honorius,</speaker>
                  <l>if I lov'd thee</l>
                  <l>So much here; I ſhall more hereafter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No;</l>
                     <l>Now comes the period of our friendſhip; and</l>
                     <l>Of what concerns, us but our memory.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>There's nothing after death; and death it ſelf is nothing,</l>
                     <l>At leaſt in all reſpects to us; for whilſt</l>
                     <l>We are, death is not; and when death is,</l>
                     <l>We are no more; and therefore nothing more</l>
                     <l>Can us concern, or humane nature, when</l>
                     <l>Our groſs and airy parts are ſeparated.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>—But the immortal ſoul</l>
                  <l>Of the renown'd <hi>Honorius</hi> ſhall embelliſh</l>
                  <l>The heavens; where it ſhall give, and receive</l>
                  <l>New light and luſtre, and the juſt reward</l>
                  <l>Of his ſo gloriouſly tranſacted life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I ne'r indulg'd my ſelf the libertie</l>
                     <l>Of any vice, as odious in its nature.</l>
                     <l>I ever honor'd virtue for her ſelf;</l>
                     <l>And payd the tribute of my worſhip to</l>
                     <l>Th' immortal Gods, as due to thoſe high powers;</l>
                     <l>Not for reward, or puniſhment; me thoughts</l>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:59228:32"/>
                     <l>That was, like Merchants, to conditionate</l>
                     <l>Irreverently with thoſe celeſtial powers.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>So I preſerv'd my conſtancy of mind,</l>
                     <l>Dejected never by ſuperſtitious fears,</l>
                     <l>Nor puſt up, and exalted by falſe hopes;</l>
                     <l>But ſtill in even balance.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>To them</hi> Fulvia <hi>and</hi> Aurelia.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>—How importunly here</l>
                     <l>Theſe women enter, to diſturb us in</l>
                     <l>Our paſſage to eternal happineſs,</l>
                     <l>Th' Inheritance of noble ſouls. <hi>Ful. Aurelia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Theſe men, deſerted of their former valor,</l>
                     <l>Have now recourſe to falſe opinions of</l>
                     <l>Philoſophers, and Pedants; and would fain</l>
                     <l>Perſwade themſelves, that death's no miſerie;</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But know it is of all the laſt, and greateſt;</l>
                     <l>Horrid, and terrible in her own nature;</l>
                     <l>As contrary to the enjoyment of</l>
                     <l>This pleaſant light; of which He now deprive you.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>—Impure creatures be gone.</l>
                     <l>The earth doth many monſters generate;</l>
                     <l>So does the ſea; yet nothing can produce</l>
                     <l>So miſchievous in nature, as a woman,</l>
                     <l>Purſuing her revenge, and ſcorning honor.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Mankind ſhould have been propagated from</l>
                     <l>Some other origine, and not from this;</l>
                     <l>The fatal ſource, the occaſion, and cauſe</l>
                     <l>Of all his miſeries, and ſervitude.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou baſe reviler of that ſex, which gave</l>
                  <l>Thee life with hazard of her own, haſt here</l>
                  <l>Extinguiſht quite all ſenſe of that compaſſion,</l>
                  <l>Which I, methoughts, felt moving in my breſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aurelia,</hi> what pleaſure 'tis to ſee</l>
                  <l>Them thus tormented in their rage: if there</l>
                  <l>Were any peace in death, 'twill make their death</l>
                  <l>Leſs peaceable; But you great Generals,</l>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:59228:32"/>
                  <l>Deep Polititians, and prime leaders in</l>
                  <l>Affairs of War and State; who fill'd the world</l>
                  <l>With ſo much noiſe, tumult, and bloud, with what</l>
                  <l>Thoughts can you now reflect upon your ſelves?</l>
                  <l>Arm'd yeſterday with numerous legions; now</l>
                  <l>Thus circumvented by the ſtratagem</l>
                  <l>Of us poor ſilly, ſimple, virtuous women.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>It is my glory, not a reproach to me</l>
                  <l>To have ſuch impious creatures ſeek my death.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>Which thou wilt undergo with high regret;</l>
                  <l>I know thy ſoul enamour'd on thy body</l>
                  <l>(Th 'object once of my love, as now of hatred)</l>
                  <l>Cannot but with great indignation quit</l>
                  <l>Her lovely, pleaſant, and delightful manſion.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>Not when ſhe ſees the neighborhood infeſted</l>
                  <l>With ſuch infectious peſtilent diſeaſes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>She muſt when ſhe no benefit can find</l>
                  <l>In death, accompany'd with infamy;</l>
                  <l>Which if ſhe have a being, will torment her;</l>
                  <l>If not; then nothing will remain of thee</l>
                  <l>Hereafter, but an odious memory.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>Let us, as it becomes us, go, and die.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>Death's our admiſſion into liberty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>Th' entrance into confuſion, and darkneſs,</l>
                  <l>Out of which no man ever found his way.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <p>The eaſe of troubled minds.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <p>Their only horror.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>The ſafe port of the virtuous.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>Th' only rock,</l>
                  <l>Which human nature ever apprehends.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>None but ſuch impious creatures, as thou art;</l>
                  <l>Who nor in life, nor death can have repoſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>Come let us die th' examples of true virtue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <p>The ſacrifices of my furious rage.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <p>We'll freely meet our death.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>Your execution,</l>
                  <l>Where you ſhall fall the trophies of my triumph.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <l>The types of honor; how happier 'tis to die</l>
                  <l>So, then like you, to live in infamie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>All after death incertain is: in life</l>
                  <l>No ſuch felicity as our revenge.</l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:59228:33"/>
               <head>ACT. V.</head>
               <stage>Aurelia diſguiſ'd.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O Thou bright glorious morning;</l>
                     <l>Thou oriental ſpring-time of the day,</l>
                     <l>Who with thy mixt vermillion colors painteſt</l>
                     <l>The Skies, theſe Hils, and Plains: thou doſt return</l>
                     <l>In thy accuſtom'd manner; but with thee</l>
                     <l>Shall ne'r return my wonted happineſs.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Here thou reduceſt back with thee, the early</l>
                     <l>Light, and the golden Planet of the day,</l>
                     <l>To revive, and illuſtrate with his preſence</l>
                     <l>The troubled world: thou chaſing noiſome darkneſs,</l>
                     <l>And clouds of diſcontent, illuminat'ſt</l>
                     <l>All hearts with joy and chearfulneſs but mine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>From thy approche all things receive below</l>
                     <l>New face, and reſtoration: The uſurping</l>
                     <l>Seas, which devour the innocent, become</l>
                     <l>Calm in their channels; the rebellious winds,</l>
                     <l>Publick diſturbers of the peace of nature,</l>
                     <l>Find and give reſt to the other elements.</l>
                     <l>All beaſts of rapin, Lions, Wolves, and Tygers,</l>
                     <l>Have their repoſe: Only a guilty mind</l>
                     <l>No cure, no peace, no reſt ſhall ever find.</l>
                     <l>Here in my breſt, as in her loathed cell,</l>
                     <l>Eternal horror will for ever dwell.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>To her</hi> Sophonia <hi>diſguiſ'd like an Eunuch.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>—O <hi>Sophonia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Since laſt night parting, we our habits chang'd</l>
                  <l>In this diſguiſe, theſe eyes have known no ſleep.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Soph.</speaker>
                  <l>Nor will not, Madam, if you keep them open</l>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:59228:33"/>
                  <l>Thus to your tears: mine are long ſince dried up;</l>
                  <l>Unleſs they'r ſuch, which have ſo many years</l>
                  <l>Continually diſtill'd within my heart.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>—O I ſhall ne'r ſleep more:</l>
                  <l>The cleer ſun-ſhine of my ſerener dayes,</l>
                  <l>In a ſhort moment vaniſhing, is here</l>
                  <l>Succeeded by a fearful night of horror,</l>
                  <l>Which will ne'r know a ſetting, but in death.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Soph.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy tender years, <hi>Aurelia,</hi> know not</l>
                  <l>The nature yet of death; it is ſo lately</l>
                  <l>From me thou learnſt to live.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>And have not the</l>
                  <l>Curſt fruits of this laſt paſſage of my life</l>
                  <l>Moſt rarely anſwer'd the bloſſoms of thy hopes</l>
                  <l>Of me? e're that my virgin honor</l>
                  <l>Were loſt, thus to contaminate my ſelf</l>
                  <l>With ſo deteſtable a parricide.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Soph.</speaker>
                  <p>Deſire of revenge tranſported you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>—Which the immortal Gods</l>
                     <l>Permit us never to execute our ſelves.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O what infernal torments equal mine!</l>
                     <l>Hating to live; I am afraid to die;</l>
                     <l>Yet ne'r can hope eaſe to my miſerie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now ſince, I hear, my Brother <hi>Lucius</hi> fell</l>
                     <l>Only by the unlucky chance of war.</l>
                     <l>O the moſt cruel nature of my Father!</l>
                     <l>Thus to abuſe my credulous ignorance.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Soph.</speaker>
                  <p>Madam, did he inform you otherwiſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes; and perſwaded me that <hi>Florus</hi> kill'd him</l>
                  <l>With his own hands in cold bloud after battel;</l>
                  <l>And thus deluded, gave me the curſt employment</l>
                  <l>Of cutting of this General in his Camp;</l>
                  <l>The only perſon which I lov'd, of whom</l>
                  <l>I had the fortune to be lov'd again.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Soph.</speaker>
                  <p>It was unjuſtly done, thus to deceive you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>'Twas his inſatiate thirſt of human bloud;</l>
                  <l>Which, ſince I find increaſing with his age,</l>
                  <l>I have thought of the effuſion of ſome,</l>
                  <l>Which if not ſatisfying, will delight</l>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:59228:34"/>
                  <l>Perchance his ſtrange capricious appetite.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Soph.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſcarce know what this language ſignifies;</l>
                  <l>I hope you think not by ſome greater ſin</l>
                  <l>To waſh away the leſſer; Madam,</l>
                  <l>Your virgin tears will beſt perform this office.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No; my offence is of a deeper ſtain,</l>
                     <l>And muſt be waſht in bloud: I have alreayd</l>
                     <l>Thought of the way, and fixt my reſolution.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>In this diſguiſ'd habit I'le tel my Father,</l>
                     <l>That I the fatal executioner</l>
                     <l>Have been of his <hi>Aurelia,</hi> on pretence</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Valentius</hi> had diſcover'd my deſigne:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now ſtreight I know his rage will prompt him to</l>
                     <l>Kill me with his own hands; ſo that I ſhall</l>
                     <l>Immediately the proper trophy fall</l>
                     <l>Of the moſt injur'd <hi>Florus</hi> funeral.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And, if the bloud of an uſurping Tyrant</l>
                     <l>Be ever the moſt grateful ſacrifice</l>
                     <l>To the immortal Gods, as certainly</l>
                     <l>It is, I hope that mine deriv'd from him</l>
                     <l>Will prove an acceptable offering.</l>
                     <l>The man whom I lov'd beſt, he made me kill.</l>
                     <l>Her bloud whom he loves beſt, I'le make him ſpill.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ye Gods, look down then with propitious eyes</l>
                     <l>On him the Prieſt, and me the Sacrifice.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Soph.</speaker>
                  <l>I am at preſent in an ill condition</l>
                  <l>To give, or take advice, having reſolv'd</l>
                  <l>Not to outlive the ſetting of this Sun.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sophonia,</hi> it is not fit that you</l>
                  <l>Perform the pennance of anothers crime.</l>
                  <l>Is mine ſo great? or are the Gods ſo cruel;</l>
                  <l>That nor my tears, nor bloud can waſht away.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Soph.</speaker>
                  <l>No, you more white will after this offence</l>
                  <l>Riſe and appear, then in your innocence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <p>O my <hi>Sophonia;</hi> muſt we now depart?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Soph.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes never more to meet again.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>I am not</l>
                  <l>So ſorry to forſake the light, as thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Soph.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis long ſince thou the only light haſt been</l>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:59228:34"/>
                  <l>Of theſe mine eyes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>And thou ev'n of my ſoul:</l>
                  <l>Which never felt eclipſe, but in thy abſence.</l>
                  <l>Farewel.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Soph.</speaker>
                  <p>Farewel.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Farewel my dear <hi>Sophonia:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall I once more, and this the laſt time joyn</l>
                  <l>Theſe treacherous and perfidious lips to thine?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hoſtilius.</speaker>
                  <l>I wonder I have no intelligence</l>
                  <l>From my <hi>Aurelia:</hi> my too forward fears.</l>
                  <l>Would fain perſwade me that ſhe has miſcarri'd</l>
                  <l>In my laſt enterpriſe: I muſt confeſs,</l>
                  <l>Th' employment was of a ſtrange nature, to</l>
                  <l>Make her conſpire, and act againſt the perſon,</l>
                  <l>Whom above all mankind ſhe lov'd thee moſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>To him a Meſſenger, and</hi> Aurelia <hi>diſguiſ'd.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, here's a perſon from the enemy's Camp</l>
                  <l>Deſires ſpeedy admittance.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hoſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Let him enter.</l>
                  <l>Some happy news, I hope now, from my daughter.</l>
                  <l>Sir, your buſineſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>It is of ſuch importance,</l>
                  <l>That 'twill require privacie to hear it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hoſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Leave us alone; firſt tell me who you are.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>My name is <hi>Oppius,</hi> and I am the Son</l>
                  <l>Of a Captain of the Praetorian Cohorts:</l>
                  <l>My Meſſage to your Majeſty is concerning</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aurelia</hi> the Princeſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hoſ.</speaker>
                  <l>O let me</l>
                  <l>Embrace thee; not a meſſenger from heaven</l>
                  <l>Could be ſo welcome.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>But I fear my news</l>
                  <l>Will not be ſo: In ſhort the horrid plot,</l>
                  <l>Which you deſign'd againſt our General</l>
                  <l>Has been diſcover'd; and <hi>Aurelia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Not like a lawful enemy, but like</l>
                  <l>A Traitor has receiv'd her puniſhment.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hoſ.</speaker>
                  <p>How! pray tell me then what is become of her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, I by order of <hi>Valentius</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:59228:35"/>
                  <l>Have been her Executioner; and here</l>
                  <l>Behold the fatal Inſtrument; as yet</l>
                  <l>Remaining ſtain'd with her moſt guilty bloud.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hoſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Stay, let me ſee't; take this reward, for thy</l>
                  <l>So civil meſſage, civilly deliver'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Stabs her</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Enought; enough <hi>Hoſtilius;</hi> I have</l>
                  <l>What I expected: I am thy <hi>Aurelia.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hoſ.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aurelia!</hi> ah my <hi>Aurelia;</hi> what has made thee draw</l>
                  <l>This puniſhment upon thy ſelf, and me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sir, I methoughts had left no other way</l>
                     <l>To waſh away your horrid guilt, and mine</l>
                     <l>In the effuſion of the bloud of <hi>Florus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O thou his noble ſoul, which hover'ſt here</l>
                     <l>About me, though inviſible, and canſt not</l>
                     <l>Repair to thy celeſtial origine</l>
                     <l>So ſoon; not being by thy fate, but my</l>
                     <l>Perfidious treacherie divorced from</l>
                     <l>Thy lovely body, look down on my complaint;</l>
                     <l>See how thy injury is vindicated.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Why cannot my ſoul follow thee? ſhe ſhall,</l>
                     <l>And mounted on the wings of love ſhall flie</l>
                     <l>To that part of the pure celeſtial ſkie,</l>
                     <l>Where thou ſhalt—O <hi>Florus, Florus, Florus</hi>—</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>dies.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hoſ.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ah how I have at once wounded two breſts,</l>
                     <l>And in thy death depriv'd my ſelf of life.</l>
                     <l>That bloud of thine is mine; the torments which</l>
                     <l>Afflict thy body, I feel in my ſoul. Who waits there.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>To him ſome Attendants.</stage>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Though this young Gentleman I have diſcover'd</l>
                     <l>My enemy, and as a Spie diſpatcht him;</l>
                     <l>Yet ſince he was of high Patritian bloud,</l>
                     <l>See that his body privately you burn,</l>
                     <l>And cloſe the aſhes in a marble Urn.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:59228:35"/>
               <stage>Valentius. Statilius.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, the Camp is full of the news already;</l>
                  <l>Who ſay their General was ſacrific'd</l>
                  <l>To ſatisfie ſome factions of the Court.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Were not all teſtimonies cleer againſt him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <l>No Sir, 'tis thought you were uxoriouſly</l>
                  <l>Subject to the ill government of women,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe practiſes ſhould ever be ſuſpected.</l>
                  <l>Their vows, nor oathes; their frowns, nor pleaſant looks;</l>
                  <l>Their ſmiles, nor tears ſhould conclude nothing in us.</l>
                  <l>Mans heart is ſeldom known; a womans never.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>O good <hi>Statilius</hi> compaſſionate</l>
                  <l>Me, and my years, ſo far diſtant from dotage;</l>
                  <l>Which otherwiſe might plead in my behalf.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <l>It neither can become your Majeſty,</l>
                  <l>Nor my condition longer to delude you</l>
                  <l>With idle entertainments of falſe hopes.</l>
                  <l>You are betray'd; <hi>Aurelia</hi> is retir'd</l>
                  <l>Into her Fathers Court; whom <hi>Fulvia</hi> follow'd.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Servilius</hi> has deliver'd up the Bridge</l>
                  <l>Committed to his cuſtodie; where he,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Carbo</hi> with their legions have paſt</l>
                  <l>To fight under the colors of <hi>Hoſtilius.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Sir, theſe the fruits are of the entercourſe</l>
                  <l>Betwixt the Empreſs, and her beauteous Niece.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>How long have I this viper in my boſom,</l>
                     <l>Never ſuſpected for a poiſonous creature.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O the vain hopes of my approaching triumph</l>
                     <l>In the air vaniſht! O my reputation</l>
                     <l>Betrayd by thoſe, in whoſe hands 'twas committed,</l>
                     <l>As in the ſafeſt cuſtodie.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Sophonia diſguiſ'd.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Soph.</speaker>
                  <l>So now methinks the ſtormie weathers paſt</l>
                  <l>Of my tempeſtuous life; and if a fair</l>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:59228:36"/>
                  <l>Ev'ning will crown the day, ſure I ſhall ſet</l>
                  <l>Now red and gloriouſly here in my bloud,</l>
                  <l>Which with theſe daring hands I'le now let forth,</l>
                  <l>To vindicate my honor and my worth.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>To her</hi> Valentius, <hi>as it were ſpeaking to ſome in the Tents.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Soph.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But ſee; yonder he comes, the cruel author</l>
                     <l>Of all thy miſeries; the murderer</l>
                     <l>Of thy fair reputation; and thy Son;</l>
                     <l>And as he thought of thee. <hi>Valentius,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Here thou ſhalt ſee in this Paper the motives</l>
                     <stage>Gives him a Paper.</stage>
                     <l>Of thy repentance; the defence of ſuch</l>
                     <l>Whom moſt injuſtly thou haſt put to death.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Raſh man in thy ſuſpicion; cruel in</l>
                     <l>Thy execution; from this very moment</l>
                     <l>Begin to be unhappy: yeſterday</l>
                     <l>Thou loſt thy Son; and now thy Wife, the true</l>
                     <l>Empreſs here fals before thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Stabs her ſelf.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Come in, and take this body forth. What ſtrange</l>
                  <l>Phantaſms are theſe? which ſcorn my power; and</l>
                  <l>Torment my ſight with diſmal objects; and</l>
                  <l>My ſoul with theſe reproaches. O <hi>Statilius.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>To him</hi> Statilius.</stage>
                  <l>The friend, and the Companion of thy Prince,</l>
                  <l>Thou opportunely comſt to my aſſiſtance;</l>
                  <l>If there were any: in this memorial,</l>
                  <l>By her preſented, who is now a Carkaſe,</l>
                  <l>Included is the ful malignity</l>
                  <l>Of my misfortune. Yeſterday, ſhe ſaid,</l>
                  <l>I loſt my Son, and now my Wife; but how</l>
                  <l>Can that be, if the Empreſs <hi>Palladia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So many years are paſt, dy'd without iſſue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <l>This is ſome perſon, who at the approach,</l>
                  <l>And horror of her death, diſtracted ſpoke</l>
                  <l>She knew not what.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:59228:36"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Ah how I fear this was the true <hi>Palladia.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <l>How can that be? that from the dead one ſhould</l>
                  <l>Ariſe, is more then a Poetique fiction.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>If this were falſe, I could not be ſo troubled.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir recollect your former mind, too much</l>
                  <l>Dejected with a falſifi'd appearance.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Sure 'twas the head divided from her body,</l>
                  <l>Which by <hi>Macrinus</hi> was expoſ'd before</l>
                  <l>Theſe eyes: yet I ſuſpect their faith unleſs</l>
                  <l>Where they, as here, ſhall make me miſerable.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, if you doubt your own, truſt mine; who ſaw</l>
                  <l>And had her head within theſe hands: you know</l>
                  <l>To me alone you did impart this ſecret.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis true; but why deferre I thus to read</l>
                  <l>This ſhort memorial, which may pacifie</l>
                  <l>Perchance theſe thoughts, and troubles in my mind.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <p>—Securely read it</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>My hand ſhakes, and my heart trembles at</l>
                     <l>The opening of it; and a ſuddain horror</l>
                     <l>Congeals within me all my vital ſpirits.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What horrid ſpectacle is this!</l>
                     <l>My eyes deceive me, when they ſhould preſerve</l>
                     <l>My honor; not when they ſhould make me happy.</l>
                     <l>Theſe are <hi>Palladia</hi>'s true Characters.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir you'l find the conceptions different.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Valentius reads,</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Valentius, <hi>Thy inclination to cruelty has made thee guilty of two ſtrange errors; the firſt in the injuſt condemnation of</hi> Palladia, <hi>upon a falſe ſuſpicion: who yet eſcap't the execution of thy barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous deſigne: the laſt not only in the miſtake of the crime, but the criminal. The true name of</hi> Florus <hi>was</hi> Veſpaſius, <hi>whoſe Father was</hi> Valentius; <hi>and not</hi> Arſenius, <hi>or</hi> Macrinus. Palladia <hi>was his Mother; whoſe loſs not being able to ſuſtain (for he was falſely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſ'd) ſhe made choice of a violent death. If thou deſir'ſt in thy ſelf a fruitleſs remorſe;</hi> Macrinus <hi>will give thee an account of her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violate integrity; and of other occurrents ſufficient to make thee miſerable.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:59228:37"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <l>What can a ſoul believe? when thus deluded</l>
                  <l>By ſenſes; which are thought her true informers.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O my ſuſpicions equally fatal to me</l>
                     <l>When they are juſt, or falſe! O my ſad viſions</l>
                     <l>So fear'd and apprehended without profit:</l>
                     <l>And verified in me with my ruine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Uſeleſs adviſes of the heavens; that</l>
                     <l>They only might reproach me with imprudence.</l>
                     <l>When I ſecurely thought them vain, or paſt;</l>
                     <l>I found my ignorance expoſer of them.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O thou black diſmal day; ariſing only</l>
                     <l>To ſee my honor blaſted with thy light,</l>
                     <l>And confound me in an eternal night.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Let not your Majeſtie's misfortunes triumph</l>
                     <l>In the dejecting your high noble ſpirit.</l>
                     <l>Perchance your complaints are not rational.</l>
                     <l>Why ſhould you credit to your ſenſes give</l>
                     <l>Only, when they would make you miſerable,</l>
                     <l>Refuſing when they ſatisfie your wiſhes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But ſee here happily <hi>Macrinus</hi> comes;</l>
                     <l>To diſſipate the clouds, which here involve us.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>To them</hi> Macrinus.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>O thou Protector of mine enemies;</l>
                  <l>And Traitor of the honor of my Empreſs;</l>
                  <l>And of my Son; why haſt thou thus abuſ'd me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mac.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, if it is to be compaſſionate</l>
                  <l>An error; I cannot excuſe my ſelf.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No Traitor; all circumſtances accuſe thee.</l>
                     <l>Thy very ſilence ſpeaks aloud againſt thee;</l>
                     <l>Th' accurſed ſilence, which has thus ruin'd me.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If <hi>Florus</hi> was my Son; or if <hi>Palladia</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Were innocent; why didſt thou not tell me? Was I</l>
                     <l>So great a hater of religious truth.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mac.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>In Princes with new Wives, and their Attendants</l>
                     <l>Surrounded; and with paſſions prepoſſeſt,</l>
                     <l>Truth finds her entrance doubly barricadoed.</l>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:59228:37"/>
                     <l>This, rather then to juſtifie with hazard,</l>
                     <l>Made me chuſe to ſecure the innocent.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Tell me how can <hi>Palladia</hi> be abſolv'd</l>
                  <l>From her laſciviouſneſs; when I ſaw my ſelf</l>
                  <l>Her Lovers Letter, where in amorous language</l>
                  <l>He promiſes to temperate thoſe heats<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which ſo conſum'd him, in his abſence from her.</l>
                  <l>Can any thing appear more evident?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mac.</speaker>
                  <l>Not in a form ſo near reſembling truth;</l>
                  <l>Which I unveil'd will expoſe to your view.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Calantha</hi> a <hi>Pannonian</hi> Lady, Couſin</l>
                  <l>Of th'Empreſs; loving a <hi>Roman</hi> Knight,</l>
                  <l>Call'd <hi>Plancus,</hi> then of her domeſtique Train;</l>
                  <l>Procur'd her conſent, that in Pages habit</l>
                  <l>She might repair to Court; and ſo diſcover</l>
                  <l>The ardency of her affection to him.</l>
                  <l>She changing then her perſon, and her name</l>
                  <l>Into <hi>Lucrinus,</hi> writ that Letter, which ſo</l>
                  <l>Subſcrib'd, th' occaſion was of your miſtake,</l>
                  <l>And geloſie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, which was grounded on</l>
                  <l>Such probabilities; which will exempt you</l>
                  <l>From being cenſur'd raſh.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Ah let him proceed</l>
                  <l>To tell me how he ſav'd <hi>Palladia</hi> from</l>
                  <l>My furious rage.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mac.</speaker>
                  <l>When that you had enjoyn'd me</l>
                  <l>The private execution of her, in</l>
                  <l>My village; where <hi>Calantha</hi> waited on her;</l>
                  <l>And where we all lamented our ill fortunes;</l>
                  <l>Secure of each ones innocencie; but</l>
                  <l>Could find no remedie; at laſt <hi>Calantha</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Having ſome reſpite with her tears, comes to me,</l>
                  <l>Affirming that ſhe had found out the way,</l>
                  <l>To lead us out of this dark labyrinth:</l>
                  <l>She bid me only find her in her Cloſet,</l>
                  <l>Within two hours; where I ſhould in writing</l>
                  <l>See her deſigne; and, as ſhe knew, approve it.</l>
                  <l>The time arriv'd, I went to ſee her; whom</l>
                  <l>I newly found expired, with a bloudy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:59228:38"/>
                  <l>Dagger in her right hand, and in the left</l>
                  <l>This Paper, which will clear part of the ſtory.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Statilius,</hi> read it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <p>Macrinus, <hi>thy only reſpect of vertue, and innocence, has made thee inform us of thy odious commiſſion, to make a preſent this night of my Couſin</hi> Palladia's <hi>head to the Emperor: In whoſe ſtead I beſeech thee to take mine, divided from my body. 'Tis the only, and laſt requeſt, which I dying, intreat of thee. Our age, comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xions, and features, were ſo alike, that they will remain undiſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſht in death. With this happy deluſion thou wilt incur no ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of neglecting the Emperour's ſevere Commands. And the life of the Empreſs will be hereby preſerv'd: Together with my reputation, in thus declaring I have not betray'd ſo incomparable a Princeſs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Calantha, <hi>or the Counterfeit</hi> Lucrinus.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <l>O memorable act! where ſhall we find</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Roman,</hi> or <hi>Grecian</hi> Pens to celebrate</l>
                  <l>Sufficiently the worth of this brave woman.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>How ſtrangely fortune has induſtrious been</l>
                  <l>In this my ruine. What became of <hi>Palladia?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mac.</speaker>
                  <l>Having perform'd what this Letter deſir'd,</l>
                  <l>From her with difficultie I obtain'd</l>
                  <l>Patience to live, concealed in my Village;</l>
                  <l>Till ſhe brrought forth a Son infortunate</l>
                  <l>No leſs in birth, then death, named <hi>Veſpaſius;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who yeſterday expir'd (you know the manner)</l>
                  <l>Under the name of <hi>Florus.</hi> After that</l>
                  <l>I plac't her in the family of <hi>Hoſtilius;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where ſhe was Nurſe, and Governeſs of his</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aurelia;</hi> and her great vertues, the</l>
                  <l>Delight, and admiration of his Court;</l>
                  <l>Till now impatient for the loſs of her</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Veſpaſius,</hi> ſhe uſ'd violence on her ſelf.</l>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:59228:38"/>
                  <l>Th' unhappy Mother of an unhappy Son.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <l>Theſe are events t'aſtoniſh minds at once</l>
                  <l>With grief, and wonder; horror, and amazement.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O ye Gods! was there ſo much artifice</l>
                     <l>Required to make one man miſerable?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>With what contrivance you have wrought my ruin!</l>
                     <l>O my <hi>Palladia!</hi> equally to me</l>
                     <l>Infortunate in the ſuſpicion of</l>
                     <l>Thy loyaltie; and clearing of thy fame!</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Unhappy Son! diſcover'd now my Son;</l>
                     <l>When I unworthy am to be thy Father!</l>
                     <l>Ah <hi>Florus!</hi> now thy innocence is prov'd;</l>
                     <l>When I, thy Father, am guiltie of thy murder.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <l>Great perſons, when they're injur'd in their honor,</l>
                  <l>Purſue th' offence with death; you thought you were ſo.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>O interrupt us not: thou haſt not yet</l>
                  <l>Related, how thou didſt deceive the world,</l>
                  <l>Making <hi>Veſpaſius</hi> appear for thy Son;</l>
                  <l>Nor by what error, poor <hi>Arſenius</hi> thought</l>
                  <l>Him his; which falſe belief coſt him his life.</l>
                  <l>Ev'ry one ſought the glory to be his</l>
                  <l>Father; but I the Monſter who begot him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mac.</speaker>
                  <l>Some few dayes after this your Son ſaw light,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Arſenius</hi> had a Son nam'd <hi>Florus;</hi> whom</l>
                  <l>(When he was baniſht the whole <hi>Roman</hi> Empire)</l>
                  <l>He to my care committed; but he prov'd</l>
                  <l>Of ſmall ſurvivance; which I conceal'd from him,</l>
                  <l>Making <hi>Veſpaſius</hi> paſs for his Son <hi>Florus:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Not willing to add to th' affliction of</l>
                  <l>His exile this new loſs. In the mean ſpace</l>
                  <l>(Whilſt <hi>Arſenius</hi> commanded <hi>Perſian</hi> Armies)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Teſpaſius</hi> growing up in years, and hopes,</l>
                  <l>I told him he was Son of this great Gen'ral;</l>
                  <l>Though the world thought him mine: which troubled him</l>
                  <l>To think he ſhould his firſt relation have</l>
                  <l>Sir, to your greateſt enemie; and whom,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hoſtilius</hi> raiſing tumults in the Empire,</l>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:59228:39"/>
                  <l>Reſtor'd, and made his General to oppoſe you.</l>
                  <l>What for their benefit I contriv'd, in th' end</l>
                  <l>Has prov'd the fatal ruine of them both.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O the convulſions of my diſtracted ſoul,</l>
                     <l>Deſiring, though not yet deſerving death.</l>
                     <l>O my eyes, giv'n me only for my torment;</l>
                     <l>What will ye firſt lament? the deſperation</l>
                     <l>Of a Wife; or the murder of a Son;</l>
                     <l>Or my loſt honor: And I yet alive?</l>
                     <l>Am I ſtill call'd a Prince, or Emperor?</l>
                     <l>Are theſe my eyes thought worthy of the light?</l>
                     <l>Yes; and perchance 'tis to betray me with</l>
                     <l>More fatal errors, then my former were.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Is there no curteous hand will arm it ſelf</l>
                     <l>Againſt me? but with what? with that Ponyard,</l>
                     <l>So cruelly ſtain'd in the bowels of</l>
                     <l>My Son: or elſe that which is infamous,</l>
                     <l>And wreaking yet diſtills with the chaſt bloud</l>
                     <l>Of my ſo injur'd Empreſs. Have I left</l>
                     <l>No friend, nor enemie? But why demand I</l>
                     <stage>Goes to ſtab himſelf.</stage>
                     <l>That aid, which I can give my ſelf?</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay; hold Sir,</l>
                  <l>You may die with <hi>Statilius,</hi> not without him.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Here they hold him.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mac.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, 'tis the greateſt of miſeries, to think</l>
                  <l>Your heart not capable of enduring greater.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Then let me die, to free me of this torment.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, a great Prince like you, though life he hate,</l>
                  <l>Should ſtand in oppoſition to his fate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mac.</speaker>
                  <l>And being as fearleſs to live, as die;</l>
                  <l>He ſhould at once both life and death defie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>From ſlaves we life take: not the power of dying:</l>
                  <l>Muſt my condition then be worſe then theirs?</l>
                  <l>For heavens ſake let me die, <hi>Statilius.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <l>O Sir preſerve that life, on which depends</l>
                  <l>The happineſs of all your Friends, and Subjects.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis vain to teach him pitie, who has been</l>
                  <l>So cruel to his Son, and Wife, and thee,</l>
                  <l>The brave <hi>Honorius,</hi> glory of the age.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:59228:39"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mac.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Majeſtie ſhall live, as long as I</l>
                  <l>Have force t'oppoſe your death.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Ah Traitor, haſt thou not</l>
                  <l>Confer'd ſufficient miſeries upon me,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs thou doſt prolong them? Here this dagger</l>
                  <l>Shall be the inſtrument of my revenge on thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <p>I cannot hold him: O <hi>Macrinus</hi> flie.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Here he gets out of their hands, and purſues</hi> Macrinus, <hi>who kills himſelf.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mac.</speaker>
                  <p>No: like a <hi>Roman,</hi> by theſe hands I'le die.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>He has eſcapt me.</l>
                  <l>However I will not eſcape my ſelf.</l>
                  <l>So; now I ſhall die. Oh;</l>
                  <l>But not my name, or laſting memorie.</l>
                  <stage>Stabs himſelf.</stage>
                  <l>Of my raſh and inhumane crueltie</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Statilius,</hi> —</l>
                  <l>Thy Prince bids thee farewel, and goes to know,</l>
                  <l>Since here is none, if there be reſt below.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>dyes.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Valentius,</hi> thy brave ſoul is fled, that ſoul</l>
                  <l>Which did not only animate thy body,</l>
                  <l>But the whole fabrick of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire,</l>
                  <l>Which now lyes bury'd in thy Funeral;</l>
                  <l>Such is the ſequel of ſo great a fall.</l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
